<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Great work of redemption deliver'd in five sermons at St. Paul's, and at the Spittle, Aprill, 1641 ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 195 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 109 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85648</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1787A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42330</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">36273005</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 36273005</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150077</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85648)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150077)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2228:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Great work of redemption deliver'd in five sermons at St. Paul's, and at the Spittle, Aprill, 1641 ...</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 198 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. Playford and are to be sold at his Shop in the Temple, neer the Church door,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the William Andrews Clark Memorial Library, University of California, Los Angeles.</note>
                  <note>On the passion of Our Saviour / by Dr. Soames, Vicar of Staynes.- -On Our Saviours resurrection / by Dr. Morton, bp. of Durham.--An appeal to  Gods mercy / by Dr. Potter, bp. of Carlile.--The expectation of a Christian / By Dr. Westfield, bp. of Bristol.--The imperfection of a Christian in this life / by W. Price.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Redemption --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150077:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Great Work of Redemption:</hi> Deliver'd in Five SERMONS At St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s, and at the <hi>Spittle, Aprill,</hi> 1641.</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. <hi>On the Paſſion of our Saviour:</hi> By Dr. <hi>Soames</hi> Vicar of <hi>Staynes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>II. <hi>On our Saviours Reſurrection:</hi> By Dr. <hi>Morton</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Durham.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>III. <hi>An Appeal to Gods Mercy:</hi> By Dr. <hi>Potter</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Carlile.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>IV. <hi>The Expectation of a Chriſtian:</hi> By Dr. <hi>Weſtfield</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Briſtol.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>V. <hi>The Imperfection of a Chriſtian in this Life:</hi> By <hi>W. Price</hi> B. D.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>J. Playford</hi> and are ſold at his Shop in the <hi>Temple</hi> neer the Church door. 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:150077:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150077:2"/>
            <head>The Texts of the following Sermons.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Firſt, a Sermon</hi> on the Paſſion, Job chap. 7. verſ. 20. <hi>I have ſinned, What ſhall I do unto thee, O thou Preſerver of men.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Second, a Sermon</hi> on the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, St. Matt. chap. 28. verſ. 6. <hi>He is not here, for he is riſen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Third Sermon,</hi> An Appeal to Gods mercy, Pſal. 130. verſ. 4. <hi>But there is mercy with thee, that thou mayſt be feared.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fourth Sermon,</hi> The Expectation of a Chriſtian, Philip. chap. 3. verſ. 20, 21. <hi>But our converſation is in heaven, from whence we look for our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, who ſhall change,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fifth Sermon,</hi> The Imperfect ſtate of a Chriſtian here, 1 Cor. chap. 13. verſ. 9. <hi>For we know but in part, and we propheſie but in part.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:150077:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150077:3"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough we ſhould love the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters for the word, yet ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, yea very often, men are occaſioned to love the Word by the Worth of the Miniſters that Deliver it; a cracked Bell is not good to Call men together, nor Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of cracked and blemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed Reputations fit Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to perſwade others to Holineſs, and therefore it is that the Names of theſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend and Eminent Divines,
<pb facs="tcp:150077:4"/>who ſpake and wrote theſe following Sermons are prefixt in the Title Page, that the Honour and unblemiſhed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, they have in the Churches of Chriſt, and amongſt all ſincere and pious Chriſtians, may the more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend them to thee. Thou haſt (Good Reader) here un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folded and opened the Great and Glorious Myſteries of thy Salvation, then which there is nothing more pleaſant and comfortable, more ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mating and enabling, more raviſhing and ſoul contenting to a true Chriſtian, then the frequent and moſt ſerious Meditation. Thou haſt here
<pb facs="tcp:150077:4"/>the Paſſion, Reſurrection, and the Glorious Expectation of a Chriſtian enlightned to thee, by Stars in the Right hand of Chriſt of the Firſt Magnitude. Oh! that the Light held forth in the Ignominious and pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Sufferings of thy Saviour, may give thee a true ſight and ſenſe of thy ſins, and the greatneſs of them, which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could expiate, but the Pretious Blood of the Imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate Lamb of God, and that with a Broken and Contrite heart, thou mayſt cry out with Holy <hi>Job, I have ſinned, what ſhall I do unto thee, O thou Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver of men!</hi> Oh! that the Light alſo held forth in the
<pb facs="tcp:150077:5"/>Glorious Reſurrection of Chriſt, which is <hi>Arrham Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectionis noſtrae,</hi> which is the Earneſt of our Reſurrection, may ſuſtain and ſupport thy ſpirits in theſe evill and laſt dayes, knowing that this Body of thine, now chiefly ſubject to many miſeries and calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties through the Iniquity of the Times it may be to be caſt into ſome loathſome Priſon, or put to a ſhamefull death; yet this ſame Body of thine ſhall Riſe, and that by a live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly faith, thou mayſt ſay with <hi>Job, Job</hi> 19.25. <hi>I know that my Redeemer liveth, and that though wormes deſtroy this Body of mine, yet in this Fleſh I ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:150077:5"/>ſee God with theſe mine Eyes, and not other, though my Reins be conſumed within me;</hi> yea thy hope and expectation ſhall not be cut off, but all thoſe afflictions which it pleaſeth thy good God to permit Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than or his Inſtruments to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe thee with, ſhall not be like idle Indifferents, which do neither good nor harme, but they ſhall all <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, work together for the Glory of God, and the Dear Salvation of thy pretious Soul; be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded therefore ſeriouſly to peruſe theſe Sermons, and the God of all Grace and Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation ſanctifie the Reading them to thee.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:150077:6"/>
            <head>The Introduction made by Maſter <hi>Price</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Rehearſal of the Subſequent Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Church, <hi>May</hi> 2. 1641.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was a Conſtitution of thoſe admired ſons of Juſtice the <hi>Areopagi,</hi> that ſuch as pleaded before them ſhould plead without Prefacing and without paſſion: But I muſt crave your gracious pardon if at this time I tranſgreſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond
<pb facs="tcp:150077:6"/>thoſe bounds; For I made account to have been ſo happy, as to have been an Auditor, but it fals out to be my unhappy lot now to be a Speaker; The Speaker appointed for this dayes work being the priſoner of God upon his bed of ſickneſs. His place my great weakneſs is forced to undertake, and therefore rolling my ſelf upon the Almighty Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God, I must inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to go through this difficult travel; more fit for an Angel, crowned and inveſted with eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, then a mortal man; and I am confident that my firſt ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons to this work was ſince the preaching of the Paſſion Sermon in this place; and therefore I
<pb facs="tcp:150077:7"/>hope you will not expect from me that curioſity of Introduction, elegancy of expreſſion, volubili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of tongue, or exquiſiteneſſe and readineſs in delivery, as other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe you might.</p>
            <p>A review of remarkable words or actions, it is as ancient as it is profitable: When God had done with the firſt dayes work he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peats it the ſecond day. What is the Book of <hi>Deuteronomy,</hi> but the Law the ſecond time repeated? What are the Books of the <hi>Chronicles,</hi> but a recapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulation of the Books of the <hi>Kings?</hi> What is the New Teſtament, but an open explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that which is cloſely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in the Old?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:150077:7"/>
            <p>It was the requeſt of the <hi>Jews</hi> when they heard Saint <hi>Paul</hi> preach of the Reſurrection (and the Reſurrection is the chiefeſt Argument of the Sermons I am now to rehearſe) that they might hear it again the next Lords day, <hi>Phil. 3.1.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Repetition is like unto the third and laſt concoction, that turns the meat into wholeſome and nouriſhing ſuſtenance. In a word, Repetition is a recollecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſo that I am to make a recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of theſe Sermons, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I may ſay as it is recorded of the men of <hi>Gibeath,</hi> of <hi>Benja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min,</hi> that they were ſuch good Archers, that they could ſhoot at an hairs breadth: Such were
<pb facs="tcp:150077:8"/>theſe men in their ſeveral tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent expreſſions; though their Sermons were long, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay they were tedious: ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are brief and tedious, but theſe were long and not tedious. As <hi>Plinius ſecundus</hi> ſaith of <hi>Cicero,</hi> his longeſt Orations were accounted the beſt. They were not like <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> expert in Sorcery, but like <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Peter,</hi> faithful Shepherds. They delivered not any <hi>Socinian</hi> or <hi>Pelagian</hi> doctrine in all their diſcourſes; their Bells were like the Bells of <hi>Aaron,</hi> and ſo they did ſound in our ears; and for the manner of the ſetting forth of thoſe diſcourſes, they were not affectatious of them,
<pb facs="tcp:150077:8"/>they ſtudied rather for Divinity then Rhetorick; for <hi>ſanantia</hi> rather then <hi>ſonantia verba,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſound then ſounding words. They were not like falſe friends, to ſpeak one word for Chriſt, and two or three for themſelves: They would transform a brazen Soul, into a lump of Clay; They would inſpire into a ſtony heart, a ſoft and melting heart. The memory of <hi>Cirus,</hi> that knew the names of all the Souldiers in his Army; of <hi>Themiſtocles,</hi> that did beare the names of all the Cittizens he had, were not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient ſufficiently to expreſſe the excellency of their Diſcourſes. Here was a Field full of Lillies, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Garden full of Roſes, food ſent
<pb facs="tcp:150077:9"/>down from Heaven upon you; and firſt, that that was let down and fell upon you in this place of the Lamb ſlain for our ſins from the beginning of the world, in that elegant feeling and melting diſcourſe, whoſe Foundation was layd in the 7<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> Chapter of the Book of <hi>Job,</hi> and the 20<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> verſ. <hi>I have ſinned, what ſhall I do unto thee, O thou Preſerver of men? Why haſt thou ſet me as a marke againſt thee, ſo that I am a burden unto my ſelf?</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:150077:9"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Paſſion Sermon:</hi> OR, A Sermon Preached by Dr. <hi>Soames</hi> Vicar of <hi>Stanes,</hi> and Prebend of <hi>Windſor</hi> in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Pauls</hi> Church on <hi>Good Friday, April</hi> 23. 1641.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JOB 7.20.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>I have ſinned, what ſhall I doe unto thee O thou preſerver of men?</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat theſe words are, and from what ſpirit they come, I ſhall not need to declare unto you by a Preface: the very hearing of the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:150077:10"/>Book named, and the reading of the Text, ſpeaking them ſufficiently to be the words of that famous mirrour of Saints, that old Diſciple of Chriſt, that ſame Evangelical Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch in the Land of <hi>Uz, Job,</hi> an up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right man, unadviſedly though he had ſinned, and many an unſeeming paſſion had that occaſion brought him unto by the afflicting hand of God upon him. One while you might behold him paſſionately no leſs then curſing his own birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day; quarrelling with the Sun, the Moon and the Stars, with the womb that bare him, and the paps that gave him ſuck. Moreover, you might have heard him challenge God, and to give himſelf the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: Nay, more then this, goes to lay violent hands upon himſelf, wiſhes he might dye an untimely death too, and juſtifying himſelf, ſayes, <hi>Is there any iniquity in my tongue? therefore I will not hold my
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:150077:10"/>peace, nor be reſtrained.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the midſt of all theſe clouds comes this comfortable Sun-ſhine, this Equinoctial. He now layes down the Buckler before him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom he had lift it up, with a penſive and penitent breaſt, crying out, <hi>I have ſinned, what ſhall I do un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thee O thou preſerver of men?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words conſidered particularly, the parts are three.</p>
            <p>Here is firſt, a Confeſſion of ſin; <hi>I have ſinned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, a deploration of his own ignorance, following upon that ſin; <hi>Quid faciam, What ſhall I do?</hi> Or if you will, of diſtraction and conſultation for the means of atone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; <hi>What ſhall I do?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, an imploration of him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom he had ſinned; <hi>O thou preſerver of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the firſt, he calls to mind what he had done. Secondly, confults what he ſhould do. And Thirdly,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:150077:11"/>finding no comfort in theſe, he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes himſelf to the laſt, the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the handling of theſe, I will firſt look upon the Text in general, as it may ſerve for an every dayes Information. Secondly, as it may ſerve for a <hi>Good-Friday</hi> Meditation: For in the choice of my Text I did not forget the day, which being to preſerve and keep alive the greateſt bleſſing that ever happened to the ſons of men, by him who is the Author and Finiſher of our ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it will be very acceptable not onely to point our finger to this Preſerver of ours, but our belief, and to look up unto him, and to cry unto him, <hi>peccavi, I have ſinned;</hi> What better mixture or compoſition I ſay, in reſpect of the qualification of the Comforter, of the Preſervers mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy? If I ſpeak not ſeaſonably to the day, the fault is mine, and not the Texts.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:150077:11"/>
            <p>And firſt to begin with the firſt, <hi>Jobs peccavi, I have ſinned;</hi> with reference to the perſon that made it: Firſt, <hi>Job</hi> cryes <hi>peccavi;</hi> a cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance I cannot but pauſe upon, as having ſomething of wonder in it. As <hi>Saul</hi> ſaid, <hi>Is this thy voice my ſon David?</hi> So may I ſay, Is this thy voice holy <hi>Job?</hi> Thou that ere while ſpoke in ſo different a ſtrain, that ſo juſtified himſelf before his Maker, is it come to no better nor worſe then a <hi>peccavi?</hi> Whence we may learn, that he that pleads with God, be he whom he will, muſt come home at laſt with a <hi>peccavi.</hi> I ſay, with God, and not with men; with men we muſt often plead for our innocency: It was <hi>Samuels</hi> caſe, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.3. <hi>Whoſe Oxe or Aſſe have I taken?</hi> It was <hi>Davids</hi> caſe, <hi>I am innocent.</hi> And ſo it was <hi>Jobs</hi> caſe here, <hi>If I have rewarded evil, &amp;c.</hi> he holds his integrity with both his hands; but when he comes to plead
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:150077:12"/>with God, then he lets go his hold, then he cryes <hi>peccavi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Holy and righteous <hi>Job,</hi> a man ſo miraculous in the Book of God, ſet up as a pattern of patience; a man in whom the Devil could not find an hole; it was the flower in his Garden, for which he ſtands upon Record, his managing of this very cauſe, ſaith he, I am faulty; and as here, ſo he is elſewhere; and as with him, ſo with all mankind: I have ſinned here, ſaith <hi>Job,</hi> and it is not to be wondred at; and the reaſons are.</p>
            <p>Firſt, in that all-ruling direction of God.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in the exactneſs of that rule by which God doth meaſure. <hi>I ſeem ſometimes,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtin, a ſtraight man in mine own eyes, but when thou comeſt to lay me by the rule of thy Law, I find my ſelf to be very crooked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a word, thirdly, it lyes in the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:150077:12"/>unavoidable infirmity that remains in our beſt actions that ever we have done or can do: I ſay, the beſt of us all, take it, and look to it, and conſider how coldly, how ſiniſterly, how diſadvantageouſly to the glory of God, ſhould he compare it with what we ſhould have done, or what we might have done, had our ſtrength been anſwerable to his deſign; and we may find reaſon, as holy <hi>Anſelm,</hi> to ſay, <hi>Poteſt &amp; non poſsit placare; It may pleaſe God, and it may not pleaſe God.</hi> If he cannot ſay as <hi>Calvin</hi> when he came to dye, <hi>Alas, that all my ſickneſs hath been ſo unprofitable!</hi> Either of theſe had not ſo much fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour as <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> yet he confeſſed, and that with tears; what his imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections wanted, he begged with tears. So much for the occaſion of the confeſſion of his ſin.</p>
            <p>One word more in relation to the matter it ſelf; what it was ſo trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled him, and which cauſed that his
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:150077:13"/>heart ſmote him; was it that he had ſpoken words that were unworthy of God, and thus irreverently ſpoken of God, and opened his mouth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patiently againſt him? Theſe are the words I am to ſpeak of. Doſt thou ſpeak thus irreverently of God whoever thou be? they will prove ſad breakings to thy heart in the time of affliction, if thou openeſt thy mouth againſt him: As <hi>Job</hi> here, <hi>I will lay my hand upon my mouth, I will hear what God will ſay; for</hi> peccavi, <hi>I have ſinned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whoſoever is the ſword or the rod, God is the Author: 'Twas the ſaying of old <hi>Eli, 'Tis the Lord, let him do what ſeemeth good in his eyes;</hi> and what unthankfulneſs it will be in us to God, if that having received ſo many good things, and but one evil, we ſhould repine at it? Should we not rather with holy <hi>Job</hi> ſay, <hi>Shall we receive good at the hands of God, and not evil?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:150077:13"/>
            <p>Fourthly, it is bootleſs to repine againſt God; like the bird in the net, the more it ſtirs, the faſter 'tis caught; or the fiſh on the hook, the more it ſtirs, the more it hurts it ſelf. If to be angry with my brother, doth deſerve to be caſt into Hell, to ſpeak againſt God is to ſhoot an arrow up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, it reflects upon thy own head; upon the head I ſay, of him that ſpeaks againſt his Maker. I will leave one word to the conſideration of thoſe men, that if all things fall not out to their mind they exclaim a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God.</p>
            <p>Indeed we find the Heathens did it (when things fell out croſly) to their Gods. We read of <hi>Sylla,</hi> that he curſed his gods, and the image of <hi>Apollo:</hi> of <hi>Licinius,</hi> that he put away his gods: of <hi>Barbaroſſa,</hi> that he did revile his gods. Oh there is a true God in Iſrael, let us not expoſtulate and rail againſt him. But I could wiſh this humour had paſſed no farther;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:150077:14"/>but is it not crept amongſt us Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and that upon ſlight occaſions? We cannot be content with <hi>Sylla</hi> or <hi>Barbaroſſa,</hi> to curſe and revile our God, but with <hi>Licinius</hi> to put him away; yea, we whip him by our blaſphemies, we ſpit on him by our raſh ſpeeches. If <hi>Jobs</hi> heart akes for a few diſtempered thoughts of God, what a deal of repentance hath the horrid and execrable blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer need of? If for a few angry words <hi>Jobs</hi> heart was ſo prickt, what will become of the profane ſwearer at the day of Judgement? Much better were it for them to come in this life before God with a <hi>peccavi,</hi> as <hi>Job</hi> here in my Text, <hi>I have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</hi> So much for the deploration of his miſery.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I come to the conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion about the means of atonement with God, <hi>Quid faciam, What ſhall I do?</hi> Which words are taken ſeveral wayes in Scripture; it is taken for
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:150077:14"/>the voice of a man perplext with grief, that is, <hi>Vox clamantis.</hi> Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther while it is taken for <hi>Vox tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentis, Act.</hi> 2. It is ſaid of thoſe that were converted by Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> they were prickt to the heart, and cryed, <hi>Men and Brethren, what ſhall we do?</hi> and the Jailor being amazed at the Earthquake comes trembling to <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas, Act.</hi> 16. ſaying, <hi>What ſhall I do?</hi> Sometimes it is <hi>Vox inferentis,</hi> the voice of an Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, one that looks after help and ſuccour, that is not reſolved what to do: So the young man came to Chriſt, asking, <hi>What he ſhould do to be ſaved?</hi> Now theſe diſtinctions offer unto us this conſideration gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally; <hi>That the effects that ſin at the beſt works in a man, are ſorrow, fear and care:</hi> Or to draw three into two; <hi>His repentance and turning unto God, till God be at peace with him.</hi> To confeſs is not enough, but we muſt deplore; to deplore is not enough,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:150077:15"/>but we muſt inquire; to inquire is not enough unleſs we ſeek to him that can preſerve us: <hi>What ſhall I do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thee?</hi> And from hence I come to the next part, <hi>Oh thou Preſerver of men!</hi> It is not enough to confeſs our ſins, but we muſt deplore them and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wail them; and not onely ſo, but when a man hath committed a ſin it runs him into a Labyrinth, he knows not what to do, it fills a mans heart with tears and with grief, it puts him upon ſuch a confeſſion that it makes him mourn. This is the nature of ſin, where it is truly ſeen in the breaſt of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> in <hi>Peter,</hi> in <hi>Job,</hi> and ſo in the reſt of all thoſe ancient Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents concerning the neceſſity of this <hi>Quid faciam?</hi> In the Primitive times, in Saint <hi>Auſtins</hi> and <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians</hi> times, after any hainous ſin committed, this kind of ſorrow caſt theſe ancient Chriſtians before the feet of their Biſhops, and coſt them no leſſe then whole weeks, whole
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:150077:15"/>moneths, and whole years in bewail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their ſcandalous crimes and apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſies in ſackcloth and aſhes, beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing prayers at the doors of their Congregations, blurring their faces with tears, and their cheeks with mourning; and thoſe that had not the grace to do this were not admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Congregation. It is memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable at this day to conſider what Antiquitie required, what their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions were towards notorious ſinners, inhibiting them the uſe of all Gods creatures but bread and water for many dayes, till they came with a <hi>Quid faciam?</hi> debarred them a long time from coming to the Lords Table, and not onely to cry, <hi>peccavi Pater,</hi> but <hi>peccavi frater, I have ſinned brother, by bringing a ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal upon the whole Church of God.</hi> If you will ask the reaſon of this, they thought they came as enemies to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade the Lords Table before thus reconciled; and to let them do leſſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:150077:16"/>then this was to uſe a terrible kind of judgment, and to deſtroy them in a flattering way, as Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith. Harſh and tender years, and cruel Age wherein we live, wherein we have fancied to our ſelves ſuch a repentance as knows nothing of tears, none of theſe tears, or if any, they tarry but till the minſtrels deſcend, the flagons of wine are fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, their dainty Cates are provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; they waſh down their ſorrow in cups of wine; they applaud them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſaying, <hi>I thank God I am not in ſuch a caſe as this man;</hi> but no thoughts of their ſins, no lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for their iniquity.</p>
            <p>I might here ſhew unto you that ſorrow is never well beſtowed but upon ſin, this ſorrow will cure no other diſeaſes; I loſe my child, and mourn for it, but ſorrow will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive it; I go backward in the world, I am ſorry for it, but it makes me never the richer. I am purſued by
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:150077:16"/>an enemy, ſorrow will make no reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, but ſpent upon ſin, it is well beſtowed, here it cures. If a man caſt away his ſorrow upon his wife, his cloſet, his ſhop, he had as good waſh his houſe with ſweet water; but ſorrow this way for ſin, it will like <hi>Aarons</hi> rod eat up all the reſt of the rods. If a man forſakes his ſin without an hearty ſorrow for it, it is no kindly departure.</p>
            <p>In the next place I come unto thoſe that think there is no need of a <hi>Quid faciam?</hi> When thou ſinneſt, hither muſt thou come at laſt; though you out-ſwear it, out-drink it, out-play it, yet it will come at laſt; <hi>Citius aut ſerius:</hi> If not in the day of thy proſperity when thou waſheſt it away, yet when thou goeſt down in the world it will find thee, and like <hi>Ahab</hi> it will ſay unto thee, <hi>Have I found thee, O mine enemy!</hi> And as the <hi>Malus genius</hi> ſaid to <hi>Caius, Thou ſhalt meet me at</hi> Philippi;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:150077:17"/>which was the place where he ſhould dye. If thou heareſt not of ſin by way of ſorrow now, it will find thee at the day of thy death; if not here, yet there is a place of weeping, wail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and gnaſhing of teeth, <hi>aut peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentium lachrymas aut damnatorum;</hi> if thou heareſt not of it here, thou wilt hear of it there; and who would not rather chooſe to take his part with <hi>Job</hi> here in my Text, then to dye with ſorrow? Who would not ſtrive to turn the current of his griefs this way, then to let them run till he come to everlaſting torments? In a word, in two things <hi>Jobs</hi> pattern is to be followed: Firſt, for ſins im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly committed againſt God we muſt ſorrow, <hi>I have ſinned againſt thee, what ſhall I do to thee?</hi> which is a point to be conſidered, God will have it done to him. <hi>When you faſt,</hi> ſaith God, <hi>was it unto me? Againſt thee onely have I ſinned,</hi> ſaith <hi>David, Pſalm</hi> 51. Why, <hi>Uriah</hi> was killed,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:150077:17"/>
               <hi>Bathſheba</hi> abuſed, <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſcandalized? No: But one God is worth a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand <hi>Uriahs, Bathſheba</hi>'s, and <hi>Iſraels,</hi> and he was diſhonoured by it. Our ſorrow for ſin muſt be directed to God, for he is the Preſerver.</p>
            <p>Now I come to the ſecond point, (from the queſtion propounded in an inquiſitive manner, which was the firſt) which is this; That turning to God is not enough unleſſe we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, and confeſſion is nothing unleſs we deplore, and deploration will do us no good unleſſe we inquire; <hi>Quid faciam?</hi> and not onely inquire, but we muſt put it in execution; careful as well as ſorrowful, practical as well as inquiſitive, ſomething to be done to get us friends with God. <hi>Who can tell whether God will turn and repent?</hi> it held up the <hi>Ninevites</hi> from ſink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. When <hi>Davids</hi> faith was like fire in the embers quite covered o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and he crying out, <hi>Why art thou diſquieted within me?</hi> yet he had
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:150077:18"/>hope in God. This is that we muſt look for; but we cannot find this in the breaſt of moſt wicked men, to bring them to practiſe as God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes them: For Chriſt when he came to cure the blind man he had a queſtion to ask him, <hi>Viſuè ſanari? Wilt thou be made whole?</hi> There are many on the way ſide, that if you ask them if they will be cured of their ſore arms and legs, they will tell you no; for ſay they, we can make more of them fore then whole: So there are many that will not be made clean, nor ſorrow for their ſins, becauſe of loſing their joy.</p>
            <p>To ſpeak one word concerning this <hi>Quid faciam</hi> of <hi>Job:</hi> With the ſame breath wherein he pronounces himſelf willing to do, he pronounces himſelf at a loſt eſtate, not knowing what to do, eſpecially in the way of ſatisfaction to God, as <hi>Hugo</hi> and others do underſtand it. And ſo
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:150077:18"/>they conſider it as if <hi>Job</hi> had ſaid, <hi>O Lord, if I had to do with any but with thee, I could tell how to make ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; but to thee,</hi> qui bonis meis non eges, <hi>which ſtandeſt in need of nothing that I have, with thee between whom there is an infinite diſproportion, what can I do to thee? What are ten thouſand rivers of oil, the ſeed of my body for the ſin of my ſoul? I can bemoan, I can conſult, I can reſolve upon what thou wilt direct me, but more then this I cannot do, nor any ſatisfaction worthy of thee:</hi> Giving us to underſtand, that whatſoever may be thought of ſatisfaction to God, if we do propoſe an equivalence, it is a dream. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it may be neceſſary to make ſatisfaction fraternal, if we have done him any hurt or wrong, to reſtore to him; or material, to our Mother the Church, for giving ſcandalous examples, that the ſcandal of the Church may be ſome way repaired: but for the ſatisfaction to God, it is
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:150077:19"/>too great a thing to be done. <hi>Job</hi> knew not what to do; he makes his query, he turns himſelf to God, and becomes an humble ſuppliant for mercy, leaving all hopes of merits or ſatisfaction: <hi>What ſhall I do unto thee, O thou Preſerver of men?</hi> So that I come to the third branch, his reſolution. We have had <hi>Job</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing, bemoaning, bewailing and inquiring, hear him now reſolving what to do; he addreſſes himſelf to the throne of the divine Majeſty, <hi>What ſhall I do, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe words are not onely ſpoken conſultively to God as to an Oracle for advice, but reſolutely; whence we have a good point: That in things concerning God it is good to go to, to addreſſe our ſelves to God, eſpecially in matters of ſatisfaction; but that's not all, but to go to him as to a Sanctuary. <hi>Job</hi> here flies to God as to a City of Refuge, to a Caſtle of defence, as the Malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:150077:19"/>were wont to the horns of the Altar, ſo doth <hi>Job</hi> after his ſin to the Preſerver of men.</p>
            <p>And here it is to be handled whom <hi>Job</hi> means by the Preſerver; doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he whom in moſt places he calls his Redeemer, and here was the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of his faith, without all perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture the ſame: It muſt needs be the ſame, for how can they call up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him in whom they have not belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved? and ſo here <hi>Job</hi>'s prayer is preferred to him in whom he had believed, the Preſerver of men: And in handling of this there are two things offered to your conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
            <p>Firſt, how well this title of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver of men doth agree with him to whom <hi>Job</hi> prayes.</p>
            <p>Secondly, how well the medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Preſerver did fit <hi>Job</hi> in the caſe wherein he was. Firſt, I ſay, how well this title of Preſerver doth ſuit with God, how well God had
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:150077:20"/>deſerved it at <hi>Jobs</hi> hands to be known by the name of the Preſerver of men, and how well by the world in general, the whole frame, maſſe, and pillar thereof; how well at the hands of that part of the world called men; how well, I ſay, at men, ſuch as <hi>Job</hi> was. It is admirable to conſider how true God is to the title of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver of men; he hath not onely ordained means to ſupply the needs of every man, and the care of every man in preſervation of himſelf; alſo his Angels about us, he gives his Angels charge over us; alſo the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of every one to take care of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and not onely ſo, but the care of our Anceſtors to preſerve our li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, they pitched our Tents; not onely his care of great men to ſet them over leſſe; he ſaith to Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates and Miniſters, <hi>Keep this man ſafe, thy life ſhall go for his;</hi> he is thy preſerver every way, and hath ſtill reſerved to himſelf the name of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:150077:20"/>chief Preſerver: He is <hi>Archiepiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus, the chief Biſhop of our ſouls,</hi> he hath taken upon him all the names of ſalvation; he is our Father, and Mother, and Brother, and Husband, and Keeper, to ſhew how true he is to the title of Preſerver: and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times when God looks like a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyer, when God comes to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy us for our ſins, he ſtaies and pauſes, and ſtrikes, with much lenity, to ſhew to all the world that he fights not with the perſon but the ſin, his Commiſſions are againſt the diſeaſe, not the patient; Chriſts ſcourges were not to deſtroy the Temple, but to clear it. We may compare them to <hi>Davids</hi> battel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Abſalom,</hi> where there is a charge goes along, <hi>Do the young man no harm.</hi> God hath given every chaſtiſement this warning, <hi>Do the man no harm.</hi> I will ſhew one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; When <hi>Joab</hi> was ſent to take <hi>Sheba</hi> the ſon of <hi>Bichri,</hi> when he
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:150077:21"/>came to deſtroy the City whereto he fled, a wiſe woman deſired to ſpeak with him, and asked him why he would deſtroy the City? who told her; whereupon ſhe required the head of <hi>Sheba</hi> to be caſt over the wall to him: With the ſame er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand God comes to us when he looks upon us as if he would deſtroy us, he calls upon us to deliver up the ſon of <hi>Bichri,</hi> the ſins that are within us, deliver them up, and he will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy you. Look upon all his affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions whenſoever that it happeneth, ſo that he cannot but he muſt puniſh; do but conſider with what unwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe God comes, with what relu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctancy; when he holds up his hand to ſtrike, he yet ſtaies to ſee if there be any to ſtand in the gap, or to hold him, <hi>Amos</hi> 11.16. <hi>How ſhall I give thee up, O Ephraim? how ſhall I deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thee? how ſhall I make thee as Admah or Zeboim?</hi> He doth it as though it went againſt him, he draws
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:150077:21"/>and brandiſhes; nay, when his ſword is in his hand he looks about him to ſee if there be any to hold his hand that he might not deſtroy; and yet when he doth puniſh, he doth not ſuffer his mercy to be quite gone, and when he is cutting, he ſtill pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves. I ſhould have told you how well God deſerved the name of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver at the hands of <hi>Job;</hi> in the fail of all <hi>Job</hi>'s comforts, in the fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all other preſervers. His wife that ſhould have preſerved him, ſhe counſelled him to curſe God and dye, and his friends that ſhould have comforted him, were miſerable comforters. The Devil let looſe upon him, his brethren ſtood afar off, they ſtood at a diſtance, his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants they were no preſervers, he called, and they did not anſwer, the very children did mock and ſlight him: Now God preſerved him from his wife, his children, his friends, his ſervants, from the Devil, yea,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:150077:22"/>from his own ſelf; he was going about to ſtrangle himſelf, to have laid violent hands on himſelf, and God preſerved him from the Devil that went about to deſtroy him; well might <hi>Iob</hi> know God by that name the Preſerver of men; well might the meditation of the Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of men become <hi>Iob</hi> at this time, in ſuch a condition, when his ſins were in his thoughts, when he was in his perplexed condition, in his affrighted condition, it was <hi>Iobs</hi> beſt way at that time to ſtir up the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Gods preſerving him. What face ſoever God ſet upon it, and whatſoever his uſage was to him, yet certainly that God with whom he was making his peace, to whom he made his confeſſion, he was a Preſerver of all his creatures, of men, and amongſt men ſinners, <hi>Pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cavi, I have ſinned, and what ſhall I do?</hi> I call this <hi>Iob</hi>'s meditation; theſe two muſt depend together;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:150077:22"/>the thoughts of a mans ſin, and the thoughts of our Saviour, think of our ſin and of our Saviour; at this time 'tis true there are many that think this Preſerver doth not ſo well agree with God, as when they ask me, how I conceive of God that is a flaming fire to render vengeance, and that he muſt ſo be remembred. I anſwer, we muſt ſo remember God, as not to forget that he is a merciful God, neither to think ſo deeply of our ſins, as to forget the thoughts of our Saviour; not as <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das,</hi> when he had betrayed Chriſt he confeſſed he had betrayed inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent bloud, and reſtores the pieces, but all ended in <hi>ſtrangulavit ſe;</hi> he hang'd himſelf, he had forgotten the Preſerver of men; it is no more then needs to be to have our ſins al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes before us. <hi>David</hi> labours to aggravate his ſin, it is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood not without the propoſal of Gods mercy; ſo we muſt look upon
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:150077:23"/>ſin by the light of Gods Word, and not by Satans falſe glaſſes. Gods manner of revealing ſin, and the Devils are contrary. God cures us like a good Phyſician, that takes a man into a cloſe room and applies medicines; the Devil doth not ſo, he carries him into the cold air, he goes about to kill him: take heed of looking upon ſin with the Devils glaſſe, unleſſe you have your friends about you, the Goſpel, and all the promiſes of it, that if he offers to wrong you, you may call them in. And therefore the Uſe ſhall be, that we look not upon ſin with both our eyes, but caſt one eye upon ſin, and another upon our Saviour, not ſo as to look through him, or beyond him, but with the faith of <hi>Abraham,</hi> he can ſee through a barren womb, and through a killing ſword his numerous poſterity. A good Chriſtian he can look beyond them all, and ſee Chriſt at Gods right hand to bring him
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:150077:23"/>ſafely to Heaven. This was <hi>Jobs</hi> prayer and caſe upon a dunghil, through the ill counſel of his wife, through the diſcomforts of his friends, through the deſpiſings of his brethren, through the machina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Devil, through the ſligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of his ſervants, and through the contemning of children, yea, through the evil temptations of his own heart he can ſee God his Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; and this muſt be our courſe, when our underſtandings will go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with the Devil, when our ſcant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſouls ſhall imagine that we hear God ſay unto us, <hi>Go you unprofitable ſervants,</hi> and <hi>go you curſed;</hi> and when we can ſee nothing but death and Hell, then remember <hi>to ſtand ſtill and ſee the ſalvation of God,</hi> remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber him that is the Preſerver of men; a duty that invites you to fix your thoughts upon this Preſerver of men. I am now come from the date of my Text, and am now
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:150077:24"/>to come to the work of the day, and it doth much concern you to fix your eyes and intendments upon this Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver of men, general contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plations of Gods preſerving; you have heard already how well God deſerves from the world and the hands of men in particular, the word of Preſerver: And thus I have done with it as it is an every dayes meditation; but I muſt not ſhake hands and take leave of my Text ſo; you know how well this dayes work will agree with it, which hath long ſince invited me unto it, had I an heart or words anſwerable unto it: but alas what words can be uſed, or what tongue can utter it: that which my heart cannot reach to, how can my tongue utter or expreſs:
<note n="*" place="margin">Si mihi ſint centum linguae, ſint ora<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> vox—</note> Which of you can tell me? <hi>Oh my God,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtin, Da mihi de miſericordia,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Give me of thy mercy that I may
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:150077:24"/>ſpeak of thee, ſpeak in me that I may ſpeak of thee.</hi> A work above any humane power to make any tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable demonſtration of, had I as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tongues as there are ſtars. Were there a Councel called of all the Angels in Heaven to conſult of it, and among them one choſen to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it, all their tongues, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, and imaginations infuſed into him, had he all the learning and eloquence that ever was or can be attained, were he to ſtand in my place at this time, how ſhould I ſee him gravell'd, puzzell'd, and faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd, and founder'd, and non-pluſt? how ſhould I hear him call for more tongues, for more eloquence? how ſhould I hear him cry with <hi>Eſay, Quis enarrabit? Who ſhall ſhew his works?</hi> Should I not hear him cry out with <hi>Moſes, Ego ſum puer, I am a child?</hi> with <hi>David, This knowledge is too wonderful for me?</hi> Whether I look upon the work of this day, or
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:150077:25"/>upon God poſitively in the contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of it, in the execution or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, with reference to the object, the parties that it may concern, or with reference to the work it ſelf, or with reference to the manner of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, the condition from whence we were redeemed, and the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to which we were brought; it is beyond human invention to give any tolerable deſcription of it. I think this matter will do better in applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion then in amplifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<note n="*" place="margin">Ora mille flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia melle.</note>.</p>
            <p>If we look upon it firſt of all comparatively, comparing it with other dayes, and paralleling it with other preſervers: What are they other preſervers, and other ſaviours? We know where to finde them. Shall we piddle out the time with the preventions of the ſufferings of particular men? what need we make mention of the children of Iſraels deliverance out of <hi>Aegypt?</hi> our own
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:150077:25"/>deliverance from the Spaniſh Invaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Eighty eight, or of the fifth of <hi>November.</hi> I charge you, as the Prophet <hi>Zachary</hi> ſpeaks on another occaſion, not a word of them, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Eighty eight, nor the fifth of <hi>November.</hi> We may parallel this dayes deliverance with the work of the Creation, there <hi>Dixit &amp; factum eſt, He did but ſpeak and it was done,</hi> here it coſt many ſweatings and drops of bloud; this was the maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece of Gods workmanſhip. There God gave me to my ſelf, here him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to me. There was the work of his finger, here of his arm, <hi>With a mighty and out-ſtretched arm hath he gotten himſelf the victory.</hi> There he made me like unto himſelf, here he makes himſelf like unto me. There he made me, but here he remade me; this exceeds the whole Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, take the whole Creation of the world together either in the contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of it, or in the execution of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:150077:26"/>it. In the contrivance, had our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour gone no farther this day then to have deviſed the means how we might be reſtored, it had been mercy enough, but to call the depths of his Counſels, to deviſe a way how to puniſh ſin, and to ſave the ſinners, to beſtow Hell upon the ſin, and Heaven upon the ſinner, how to compound an infinite Juſtice and an infinite Mercy: Had our Saviour gone no farther but found out the way, and ſaid, <hi>Sons of men, I ſee you are utterly loſt and undone, and I could wiſh that I could help you, but I counſel you to do thus and thus, ſee what you can do to appeaſe my Fathers ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, I ſhould be very glad to ſee you do well,</hi> and the like; could all the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels in Heaven have helpt us? ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly no: But himſelf to be both the contriver and executor, not onely to finde out the means, but to be the means, to call the depth of his Counſel together, to ſave the man,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:150077:26"/>and damn the ſin, to ſend one to Hell, and the other to Heaven: Oh admirable Love!</p>
            <p>Again, conſider who is the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver, the ſubject that did it, who would ever have looked to have him come down from Heaven? Who would have thought that he would have clothed himſelf with the rags of our mortality, and have come down, who was the delight of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, the darling of Heaven, the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved of his Father? It is a greater humiliation then for the greateſt Emperour in the world to become a worm, or a fly, or a grain of duſt, and all this for a creature ſo ill-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving, in whom there was neither beauty, nor comelineſſe, or favour, the things that make men favourable with Princes; nay more, when we were enemies, and in the acts of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtility, dead in treſpaſſes and ſins, worms and no men, yet he came to ſave us, even us men.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:150077:27"/>
            <p>It was the ground of a worthy me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation of a reverend Father, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Sampſons</hi> being brought to ſo much miſery for <hi>Dalilah: Oh mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable Sampſon,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>what made thee to ſpend thy deareſt bloud for an harlot, for Dalilah?</hi> How can I ſufficiently wonder at this mercy, not for an harlot, but for worſe then an harlot, for ſuch wretches as we are? and the keeping us from ſuch a ſtate, and bringing us to ſuch a ſtate; from ſuch an eſtate, an eſtate of ſin, when we lay not onely <hi>in pulvere,</hi> but <hi>in ſanguine,</hi> in the duſt, yea in our own bloud, not onely wounded, but wounded to death, yea dead; was that all? no; <hi>pereuntes, periſhing, Ezek.</hi> 16.6, 9. children of perdition, loſt, and the worſt kind of loſt too, <hi>perditi in Dei favore,</hi> loſt in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of God, <hi>perditi de benedictione Dei,</hi> loſt the bleſſing of God, no hope of any thing, but <hi>go you curſed</hi> was our next doom; nay, utterly loſt,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:150077:27"/>and yet recovered by him out of that condition; and into what a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition from all this miſerable and loſt condition we were recovered, to our inheritance, recovered from the ſtate of enemies to the ſtate of friends, to the ſtate of favorites, of heirs of Heaven: all theſe together didſt thou do, Oh merciful Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver!</p>
            <p>In the next place I come to the means by which he did preſerve us, and that by the deſtruction of him that was the preſerver, a preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on deſtructive to the preſerver him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, wherein there was a neceſſity for one to come from Heaven, and he no leſſe then the Son of God, to ſtand in the place of man, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure that which he ſhould have ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for his ſin, and that ſuch a ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to ſpeak one word of it, that the whole Goſpel is little more then a compendious Chronicle of the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities that Chriſt endured in his
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:150077:28"/>life: Should I but go along from his Cradle to his Croſſe, the time would fail me, in all places; nor only upon the Croſſe, but in the Garden, yea <hi>in toto progreſſu,</hi> &amp;c. in the whole courſe of his life, in every action of it, at the hand of every perſon he converſed withal, every part of his life from the womb, nay, in the womb he was accounted by his ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed father to be but a baſtard; in his Cradle cruelly dealt withal, exiled, baniſhed into <hi>Egypt,</hi> tumbled and toſſed up and down, tempted in the wilderneſſe by the Devil. In all places, in the Temple, in the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees houſe, in the City, in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, in the wilderneſſe, within and without, abuſed by all ſorts of men, the Scribes and Phariſees, the high Prieſts and Rulers, and by the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of people; he did ſuffer in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very action: Did he preach, where had he his learning? Did he eat and drink? a man gluttonous, and a wine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bibber.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:150077:28"/>Did he keep company? a friend of Publicans and ſinners. Did he caſt out Devils, 'twas cenſured to be by <hi>Belzebub</hi> the Prince of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils. In his life, in his death, in all things; and in his ſufferings two things are remarkable: Firſt, that he ſuffered alone, he trod the wine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe alone, he ſuffered <hi>ſolus.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, he ſuffered <hi>totus,</hi> he ſuffered for his Preaching, for his works of mercy, that for which he ſhould have been applauded. The Diſciple that before hugg'd his Maſter, and lay in his arms, now for haſte left his ſhirt behinde him, he ran ſo hard, that he left his linnen garment. <hi>Thomas</hi> that before would dye with <hi>Lazarus,</hi> he is now gone. The ſons of <hi>Zebedee</hi> that forſooth could drink of the cup that he drank of, they were far enough off; not onely his friends on earth, but his beſt friend in Heaven; he ſuffered a terrible withdrawing of his countenance, he
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:150077:29"/>ſees him not as he was wont to be in his glorious Majeſty, yet ſtill he cryes, <hi>Deus meus, My God;</hi> his beſt friends on earth fled, and his beſt friend in Heaven hid his face from him: he ſuffered <hi>totus;</hi> his head buf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fetted, his face ſpitted on, his hands nailed, and his feet bored, his ſide pierced, his glorious temples crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with thorns, he led Captivity captive, to whom we pray, <hi>Lord en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter not into Captivity with thy ſervant;</hi> he to whom the Saints cry, <hi>Holy, Holy, Holy Lord God of Hoſts,</hi> he to whom the bleſſed Spirits ſing Hallelujahs to him that ſits on the Throne, upon him they cryed, <hi>All Hail King of the Jews;</hi> he that laſhed the Nations with a rod of Iron, to have his back beaten with a whip: he ſuffered in all his outward ſenſes; What taſtes he? What ſees he? What hears he? What ſmells he? What feels he? In all his faculties and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, in his underſtanding, the whole
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:150077:29"/>wrath of God; in his memory, what he was, and what he had been; in his judgment, what ſtrugling and irreſolution, <hi>Let this Cup paſſe,</hi> and let it not paſſe, he will have his will, and he will not have his will; he was aſtoniſhed, affrighted, perplexed, in. an agony, ſuch an agony wherein he ſweat drops of bloud; of the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches done to him, if we conſider <hi>ubi, where,</hi> He ſuffered at <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> the ſtage of the world, and where he did diſplay all his works of mercy. <hi>Quando,</hi> at what time, at the time of the Paſſeover, at the concourſe of moſt people, that he might be a ſcorn to all; and <hi>cum quibus,</hi> with two thieves, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them both as the worſt of the three; and <hi>per quos,</hi> by whom this was done, by his own Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, thoſe for whom this was done, ſo graceleſſe not ſo much as thanking him for what he did, when he was at his laſt gaſp upon the Croſs; beneath
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:150077:30"/>beneath him the Devil gaping for him; on the one ſide a thief revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him, on the other none but a thief; Hell wide open under him, his friends flying from him: round about him what ſees he? the earth trembling and quaking, the rocks rending in pieces, the mountains leaping, the air thundering, the clouds pouring down, the Heavens as it were burning with lightning, the Sun hiding his face, as aſhamed to ſee his Maſter ſo uſed at their hands for whom he thus ſuffered. What hears he? thoſe that did it, crying, <hi>His bloud be upon us and our children and if there be any evil in us, not to ſave us but to damn us,</hi> when an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel durſt not ſhew his head, or ſo much as peep out of Heaven upon him.</p>
            <p>A preſervation wrought by ſuch a Saviour, to free us from ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and bring us to ſuch a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by ſuch a means he ſuffered
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:150077:30"/>both in body and ſoul, I think I need not ſay more of it; doth not this deſerve to be prized as a great mercy?</p>
            <p>But becauſe the keeping of a <hi>Good Friday</hi> doth not conſiſt ſo much by the making of a Tragical relation of his ſufferings, as it doth in ſomething elſe; this is not all that is to be done. 'Tis true, our preſenting him to your eyes is no more then needs, but we muſt praiſe the Lord for his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drous works. Can we with the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites, look up to this Braſen Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent that it may cure our ſouls? Here is an object of love, of fear, of joy, of grief, of affection, and what not? There is ſomething of the ſolemnity lies in this, to conſider what God hath done for our ſouls. I gave you a taſte at the beginning, how that <hi>Job</hi> after his ſin comes home to the Preſerver of men: So this points us to the duty of the day, and that is to make uſe of Chriſts ſufferings,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:150077:31"/>and conſidering that <hi>Job</hi> in the midſt of all his ſufferings had his eye to the Preſerver of men, he deplored his ſins, and caſt his eyes upon him. I finde the holy Ghoſt more then once mentioning the duty of the day, <hi>they ſhall look upon him whom they have pierced, Zach.</hi> 12. and <hi>looking to the Author and Finiſher of their faith, Hebr.</hi> 12. looking with ſuch eyes upon him, as the lame man in the Goſpel upon <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> to have ſome good from him. Looking upon him as a Preſerver, as thoſe Iſraelites did upon the Braſen Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent to cure them, not to wink with our eyes; let no man think the work of a <hi>Good Friday</hi> to ſee him with our bodily eyes, as the Papiſts in the ſight of the Crucifix, but the eyes we are to make uſe of are the eyes of our ſouls, the beholding of Chriſt crucified in our thoughts. Take him into your hearts and ſouls, and there preſerve him, let him challenge
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:150077:31"/>a manſion room in thee, thy whole heart; Chriſt is to be made the ſole object of this day, if you celebrate his crucifying aright. What kind of object Chriſt ought to be I will deliver in few words: Our Saviour doth preſent himſelf as an object of the eye, to behold him, as an object of the ear, as an object of trouble, as an object of joy, as an object of hope; if upon our ſin, then he is an object of wonder, an object of fear.</p>
            <p>The motive of Chriſts ſufferings, it was his love, the merit of Chriſts ſufferings procures us pardon, and the end of Chriſts ſufferings was our ſalvation. Give me leave to point my finger at each of theſe, and that in a familiar way, without danger of puzling our ſelves.</p>
            <p>He ſuffered on the Croſſe, to make good our comforts, he was bound, to purchaſe our freedome. And here firſt of all, the work of the day doth
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:150077:32"/>challenge at our hands matter of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration; it is a duty the Heavens are called upon upon a leſſe occaſion: <hi>Hear O ye Heavens, and be aſtoniſhed O earth.</hi> Who is there that hath any thing of Heaven in him, let him <hi>obſtupeſcere,</hi> he amazed and wonder, it is a wonder in all the particulars of it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, to wonder at the hainouſneſs of that ſin, the nature of which was ſuch that it could no otherwiſe be expiated but thus. That which threw <hi>Adam</hi> out of Paradiſe, the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels out of Heaven, <hi>Saul</hi> from his Kingdome, that at this day pulls down Families, and Nations, and Kingdomes; that makes ſome Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions an hiſſing and reproch to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; pray God it doth not ſerve us ſo: That which doth tumble a Kingdome into the duſt, pray God it do not ſerve us ſo. It made the Son of God to bleed, and to cry, <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:150077:32"/>me?</hi> Which of us in the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt temptation to any ſin, that is, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring the price of it, could chuſe but be intreated to hold his hand? Conſider in the ſtrongeſt temptation to any ſin, it was the price of my Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours bloud. And ſecondly, this ſerves for matter of gratulation, to be thankful for Chriſts love, that he would thus ſuffer, and that we deſpair not though we find it not in our Ware-houſes, in our Cloſets, in our Chambers, in our Cheſts, in our Cupboards, or the like outward things. <hi>Potiphar</hi> looks upon <hi>Joſeph,</hi> and ſees all things thrive under him, and therefore he loves him; &amp; ſo <hi>Laban</hi> for the ſame reaſon loves <hi>Jacob:</hi> But here is Gods love, that he gave himſelf for us; that's the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond.</p>
            <p>A third Inſtruction is for admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that obligation God hath caſt upon thee: He that could have glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed in thy deſtruction, that he ſhould
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:150077:33"/>glory in thy ſalvation, what canſt thou do but rejoyce? But to won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is nothing, if we go no farther: Therefore in the fourth place, here is matter of thankſgiving, which is a duty for every Ordinance. Every ordinary bleſſing it calls for a Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phee, a Pillar, an Altar, a Song, a Sacrifice, a Chronicle; ſo did <hi>David, Moſes,</hi> and other ſervants of God. What thanks doth he expect for this dayes deliverance?</p>
            <p>If among the Heathen he that delivers his Countrey from any po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent enemies, had ſuch applauſes and acclamations, <hi>mille annos vivat,</hi> he that ſlew a thouſand of our enemies, may he live a thouſand years, may his name be precious a thouſand years: How can we pour out our hearts before God, without giving thanks for this dayes deliverance? Neither is admiration or gratulation ſufficient, unleſſe we bleſſe our ſelves in this day, in the apprehenſion
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:150077:33"/>of him that was this Preſerver, with reference to our ſins; the bloud of Chriſt hath a vertue to bind up the bleeding ſoul, and to make the bones that were broken to rejoice. Is not this a matter of admiration, gratula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and conſolation? therefore in the fear of God theſe are the thoughts that belong to this day, let your contemplations be upon what he did; theſe contemplations would preſerve us from the ſenſe of tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral calamities. When <hi>Jacob</hi> ſaw the Ladders, and the Angels aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and deſcending, he ſaid, <hi>Haec eſt porta coeli, this is the gate of Heaven.</hi> The gate of Heaven! It is well ſaith one, that Heaven hath a gate; it is well for Gods children that there is a Preſerver, that their hopes are above with him whoſe care is to preſerve things periſhing here below, among ſo many deſtructions from thoſe that cry to our <hi>Jeruſalem, Down with it, down with it even to the ground.</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:150077:34"/>There is one above who is the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver, who doth never keep back his mercy; but when things look moſt deſperately upon earth, when the enemies hope to take them at a diſadvantage, and to fall upon them when there is none to deliver them, then if we call upon him with <hi>David,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Remember the dayes of old, and thy great mercies unto me;</hi> then it is for our comfort, that after a time God will have mercy upon us. When the night is at the darkeſt, the day is neereſt at hand. When the throws of a woman in travel are the greateſt, her deliverance is neereſt. When <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaw the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the greateſt danger, <hi>Now ſtand,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>and ſee the glory of the Lord, the enemy that now threatens you ſhall ſee him no more. The earth mourned, Lebanon was aſhamed, Baſhan and Carmel have all loſt their fruit, now will I exalt my ſelf:</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, <hi>mans miſery that's my opportunity.</hi>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:150077:34"/>When things are at the worſt with Gods children and his Church, then will he ſhew himſelf a Preſerver. The comfort of Chriſts Croſſe that's comfort to a ſoul wounded with miſery. Is there any of you here this day that is at his <hi>Golgotha,</hi> with his ſtrong cryes to God in the ſight of his ſins, and the terrors of Gods wrath, at the ſight of Gods juſtice? Are any ſuch here? then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold conſolation; that his bloud this day ſhed, if thou doſt but conceive it, if there be but a true apprehenſion in thee that that bloud was ſhed for thee, 'tis enough for thy ſalvation; that thy price is paid for thee by his death on the Croſſe, when his arms were extended both wayes, as well to the thief that deſpiſed, as to the good thief; and in that prayer he put up upon the Croſſe for the worſt of his enemies, for them that nailed him, the worſt of men; <hi>Father for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give them, for they know not what they
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:150077:35"/>do. Thoſe that nail me, that crucifie me, even for them I pray.</hi> It is very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable that when the good thief ſaw Chriſts mercy extend ſo far, to the worſt of men, he reaſons thus with himſelf, What! is there mercy for theſe? why not for me? Though a thief, yet not ſuch a wretch as theſe are thus to crucifie my Saviour; <hi>Lord, remember me when thou comeſt into Paradiſe;</hi> and remember in that prayer of Chriſt, there is forgiveneſſe for thee, and in thoſe arms ſtretched out there is a receptacle for thee, in that bloud that came out of his wounds, there is cure for thee, rather then thou ſhalt dye he will dye for thee.</p>
            <p>But beloved, to enlarge the merits of Chriſt longer, you will think I ſpread this plaiſter too far, in the mean time not knowing whether we have any part in him or no. We muſt underſtand the Myſtery of Chriſt as well as the Hiſtory; there
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:150077:35"/>is ſomething to be done by way of examination, to examine what title we have to this Saviour. Look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thy own ſins, bleed for them as well as Chriſt bled for thee. Chriſt doth not actually ſave all: For the reſolution of which, I cannot give you a better anſwer then what I told you of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Braſen Serpent, that which gave them a cure, gives me a capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of this Preſerver; that which gave them a cure, was firſt, becauſe they were ſtung. Secondly, that they did ſubmit to that command that bid them look up to the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent; the like is required of every one of them that hope to have the Preſerver of men to be their Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour.</p>
            <p>Firſt, a due ſenſe of our ſins: And ſecondly, a clear ſight of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.</p>
            <p>Firſt, a due ſenſe of the ſting; the ſting of the old Serpent the Devil,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:150077:36"/>the ſin that is in our hearts. The malice of thoſe men that crucified our Saviour, was not the Authour of it, but our ſins; the Author is in thine own boſome. And this is a conſideration very requiſite and neceſſary for us, for without a ſenſe of our ſins, and a ſorrow for them, we are not neer to the knowledg of Chriſt; true ſorrow works repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. 'Tis obſerved of <hi>Job</hi> that he would confeſſe his ſins to the Preſerver of men, becauſe he had ſinned, and not for the evil of it in the general, in the groſſe, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his own ſoul, <hi>Ego, I have ſinned.</hi> Every man doth not know what belongs to <hi>Ego,</hi> to find ſin in our own boſomes. What need we complain of the evil of the times? it is quickly told whence it comes, even from our ſins. They think they are well, becauſe they have no leiſure to ſee whether it be well or ill. Their eyes are ſo caſt abroad,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:150077:36"/>ſo inquiſitive abroad, that they know not how things go at home; if we were true Zelots indeed we might eaſily ſee that the way to make the truth known, doth not lie in the ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravation of the ſins of others, in the diſcovery of the nakedneſſe of our fathers, of our mothers, and of our brethren; no, but we muſt ſtrike impartially, we may not ſpare any ſins, and we ought to rejoice if we ſee the ſword ſtrike at both; and as it cuts Superſtitious Papiſts on the one ſide, ſo the Anabaptiſtical Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaries on the other ſide; that we deſtroy what concerns us, our ſins, it is not in any invectives or libels, but the part that belongs to thy ſhare is to ſweep before thy own door, the pulling of that brand out of the fire, it lies within thee.</p>
            <p>And then again ſecondly, as it was in the ſting, ſo it was in fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the command, and looking on the Serpent, and ſo is this the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:150077:37"/>commandment we muſt follow, we muſt uſe the hand that touched the hem of Chriſts garment, ſuch a faith as was in <hi>Peter,</hi> to bring him home to our ſelves; an aſſent to the truth of God, and not onely <hi>aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentire,</hi> but <hi>applicare,</hi> to apply Chriſt to our ſelves, and alſo <hi>adhaerere,</hi> to cleave to him, as old <hi>Simeon</hi> did, not think it enough to ſee Chriſt in the arms of his Mother, but in his own arms, he would graſp him there, and hugge him there, as <hi>Iſaac</hi> could not but bleſſe his <hi>Jacob,</hi> till he felt ſome love, ſome loyalty, ſome care; <hi>and kiſſe the ſon leſt he be angry,</hi> there muſt be a care to make good Gods image in us.</p>
            <p>There are three or four Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions I would gladly make uſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this Preſerver of men: As firſt, was our Saviour the Preſerver of men? then this is in all temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons the moſt profitable balm; Shall I commit this ſin, ſin againſt him that preſerved me?</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:150077:37"/>
            <p>Secondly, is he the Preſerver of med? then in all the inhumane and cruel dealing between thee and thy neighbour, think upon it; how doſt thou reſemble the Preſerver of men, and giveſt thy ſelf altogether to ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine and deſtruction? What expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion can you have of preſervation by this Preſerver, if you be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of your poor Brethren?</p>
            <p>In the third place, is he the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver of men? and hath he done ſo much for our preſervation? This then deſerves our thankfulneſſe. Did Jeſus Chriſt dye for me, and for us all? then let us ſhew our thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe by preſerving Gods children, Gods Profits, Gods saints, Gods Revenues; let us lend our helping hand to preſerve that, and not to think any thing we have too good for them; thy work, thy life, thy la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and all little enough for them.</p>
            <p>And then laſtly, whatſoever we do in thankfulneſſe to God, ſuffer
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:150077:38"/>not his bloud, nor the price of it to be ſpilt in vain, take heed it be not ſpilt beſides us, take heed the Devil doth not go away with it.</p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> hath a ſad meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and repreſentation of this; he brings in the Devil at the laſt day coming and triumphing againſt Chriſt, with his rabble of wicked men, and but a few righteous on our Saviours ſide. The Devil ſpeaks thus: <hi>Saviour of the world, doſt thou ſee what a number I have, and what faithful ſervants they have been to me?</hi> Ego nunquam, &amp;c. <hi>I was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver whipt, nor buffeted, nor ſcourged, nor nailed, nor deſpiſed, nor crucified for any of theſe; I never ſhed a drop of bloud for any of theſe, I never pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed them a Kingdome, or any other reward, yet they were very dutiful to me. I never had a Paradiſe to premiſe them, though thou didſt ſhew me ſuch a number as here is.</hi> Oh what a ſad thing will this be! Oh therefore
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:150077:38"/>let every one think to do our Saviour this right, let not the Devil carry away this price from us; he ſuffered enough then, Oh let not him now ſuffer any more, let him not ſuffer in his Name, to be blaſphemed; in his Revenue, as Sacrilegious perſons would have him; let him not ſuffer in his Worſhip, as Hereticks would have him; let him not ſuffer in his Prophets, as <hi>Saul</hi> did, ſlaying four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore in a day, but <hi>give unto the Lord the honour due unto his name.</hi> Oh let us give him this day the honour that is due unto him, that ſince he hath given us the bloud of his Son to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve us, he may finde us one day amongſt the preſerved; and conſider that he that is proud, crowns his head with thorns, he that ſcoffs at Religion, ſpits in his face: and think upon theſe meditations;</p>
            <p>Firſt, in what a miſerable condition thou art till thou haſt gotten ſome ſign that thou art preſerved by him,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:150077:39"/>and that thou haſt ſome part in his ſufferings. I wonder that the ſouls of many men go not out rending and tearing, go not out ſtark mad, having no evidence of their ſalvation. There is no comfort without an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in Chriſt. What a miſerable parting is there both of ſoul and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, without an aſſurance that Jeſus Chriſt is thy Redeemer? Whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever thou art, or whatſoever thy eſtate is in this world, thou art a wretch, if thou haſt not a part in thy Preſerver. As <hi>Jacob</hi> ſaid, when he ſaw the Chariots and Waggons that <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſent for him, <hi>Now I ſhall ſee Joſeph, let me dye, I deſire to live no longer, it is enough Joſeph is alive:</hi> ſo ſhould we be able to ſay, Howere the world goes in other things, we know that our Preſerver is alive; whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver deviſes Satan hath raiſed, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever crimes thou haſt committed, though the Devil ſay, <hi>nec pars, nec ſors in hoc negotio,</hi> thou haſt neither
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:150077:39"/>part nor portion in this Saviour; Oh then bethink your ſelves that God is a Preſerver.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Rabbines</hi> tell us of a City of Refuge God had appointed in the time of the old Law, that there ſhould be a City of Refuge, and that the man-ſlayer ſhould flee thither, and there was a care had that at eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry turning of the way there ſtood an hand pointing out every particular paſſage to the City of Refuge, and written at the end of the hand <hi>RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FUGE,</hi> as if it ſhould have ſaid, Fly man-ſlayer for thy life, thou haſt the way before thee. What truth is in it I know not, yet it is an excellent repreſentation of every one that are ſinners; we are in the caſe of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlayers all of us, and God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed at every turning of the way a finger, at every corner of the City there is a voice that calls upon us, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, Refuge,</hi> to ſave our ſelves; while the enemy is at our back, the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:150077:40"/>Devil follows us with might and main at the committing of every ſin that he may reach us before we get to the City. God hath his voice and his finger to point us thither, it muſt be our wiſdome to go while the finger points and the voice calls. We know not how long we ſhall hear the voice of God in our Churches, let us beſtir our ſelves as they that fly for their lives, let us hear the voice of God, and gird up our loins: we ſee by every dayes example the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty of life, let us fly to him that is the refuge of ſinners, he that had his arms this day ſpread on the Croſſe to ſave all, will not refuſe thee; and that he may ſhew us his mercy who is the Preſerver of men, God of his mercy grant us, for his Sons ſake, for his mercy ſake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus this ſweet Singer of our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> this raviſhing Nightingale, or if you will, this Dove, did groan forth
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:150077:40"/>unto you the Paſſion of his Lord; he like a dexterous Phyſician did clap a plaiſter of warm bloud to your ſouls, and I hope it will prove like the bloud of Goats, qualifying you, that you will afford plyable hearts to God, and obedient hearts to him, and charitable hearts to your bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, ſeeing you have a ſhare in this Preſerver.</p>
            <p>But there lies no comfort in the death of Chriſt, if we hear not of his Reſurrection. What is it to hear of a Saviour dead, if he be not ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen? What is it to have our Surety to be in priſon? but he is out. Hence breaks the day both of his triumph and our comfort, that this <hi>Sampſon</hi> hath carryed away the gates of braſſe, this rod of <hi>Aaron</hi> hath devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red all the other rods, this God though he overcame not at the firſt, yet he overcomes at the laſt; this <hi>Jonah</hi> is now caſt on the ſhore; and this happy tidings an Angel of our
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:150077:41"/>Church brought from another An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel, and his Text was in the Goſpel according to Saint <hi>Matthew, chap.</hi> 28. <hi>verſe</hi> 6.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:150077:41"/>
            <head>A Sermon Preached by D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Thomas Morton</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Durham</hi> at the <hi>Spittle</hi> on Monday, <hi>April</hi> 26. 1641. before Sir <hi>Wright,</hi> Lord Major.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Right Honourable, Worſhipful, and beloved in Jeſus Chriſt, hearken I beſeech you with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence to the Word of God; as it is written in the holy E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſt Saint <hi>Matthew,</hi>
               </q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Chap. 28.6.</hi> He is not here, for he is riſen.</bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THeſe are the words of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of God unto two devout
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:150077:42"/>women that came to viſit the Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre of our Saviour, declaring unto them the Reſurrection of Chriſt from the dead: a Fundamental point of Chriſtianity, and the argument of theſe three dayes Feſtivity is the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of our Saviour; and this Feaſt hath obtained from <hi>Gregorie Nazianzen</hi> this acclamation, <hi>Oh Feaſt of all Feaſts! Oh Feſtivity of all Feſtivities! Oh Celebrity of all Celebrities!</hi> And therefore beloved, we are ſo much the more bound to the diſcharge of our duties for a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn and deliberate commemorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it, and you to a diligent, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout and reverent attention unto thoſe four points and parts which are deduceable out of this Text; <hi>He is not here, for he is riſen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The parts are theſe: The firſt is Logical; the ſecond Hiſtorical; the third Analogical; and the fourth Moral. The Logical thus, from the word and particle <hi>for, He is not here,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:150077:42"/>for, &amp;c.</hi> Secondly, Hiſtorical, in the words following, <hi>he is riſen,</hi> a declaration of the Reſurrection it ſelf. Analogical, from the perſon <hi>he,</hi> in the relation that Chriſt hath as Head unto all Chriſtians that ſhall be raiſed again unto everlaſting life as the members of Chriſt. The Moral, that dependeth upon the ſame words, <hi>he is riſen,</hi> becauſe it doth challenge of every Chriſtian man a conformity of life, in riſing unto newneſſe of life conformable to that Reſurrection of Chriſt, as the Apoſtle will tell us afterwards.</p>
            <p>I begin with the Logical, <hi>He is not here, for, &amp;c.</hi> His aſſertion is Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, <hi>He is not here;</hi> the proof of it, <hi>for he is riſen.</hi> This <hi>for</hi> is a cauſal term, which if it be turned into an illative, it ſtands thus; He is riſen, therefore he is not here: As if a man ſhould ſay, the ſtars they are not ſeen, for the Sun is up. <hi>Verte,</hi> the Sun is up, therefore the ſtars are
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:150077:43"/>not ſeen. The concluſion therefore of the Angel ſhould be this, Chriſt cannot be in the grave and out of the grave, not here and there, not in two places at once; and that is our preſent Theme. This do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine that I teach unto you, it was the confeſſion and profeſſion of this our Proteſtant Church alwayes, it was written in Rubrick in the bloud of the Martyrs in the days of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> both Biſhops and others, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they were called to that mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous rack of Interrogation among the Papiſts, asking them this queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, What ſay you to the bodily pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Chriſt in the Sacrament? They anſwered, he is not there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily; they proved it, <hi>for he is riſen,</hi> he is aſcended into Heaven; a reaſon, as you ſee, Angelical, this being granted that the body of Chriſt is not in two places at once, then is the foundation of all the Romiſh Maſſe utterly ruined, diſſolved into rubbiſh
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:150077:43"/>and duſt; for then farewell the bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſence, the feigned and forged Tranſubſtantiation, the groſſe oral and bodily receiving of it, the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legious ſacrificing of it, and that which is the laſt and worſt, the idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous adoring of bread in ſtead of the perſon of the Son of God, Chriſt himſelf.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſſe we may not ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that the Doctors of that Church make no anſwer to this conſequence of the Angel, <hi>He is not here, for he is riſen:</hi> Their anſwer is this, that he ſpoke not theſe words Doctrinally, but onely Morally, <hi>ſecundum modu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum,</hi> according to the capacity of the women, who might think perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture that he was riſen not out of the grave, but in the grave: a tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent falſity, as will be proved now to the contrary: As this holy E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſt, <hi>He is not here,</hi> (could he walk in the grave to <hi>Galilee?) for he is riſen;</hi> look upon the next verſe,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:150077:44"/>
               <hi>He is riſen, as he ſaid.</hi> What ſaid he? The Evangeliſt Saint <hi>Luke, chap.</hi> 24. <hi>as he ſaid to you women when you were in Galilee.</hi> Then the ſaying muſt be taken as it was told them by Chriſt in <hi>Galilee,</hi> before he was cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified. What was his ſaying? He ſaid unto them, <hi>I ſhall riſe the third day.</hi> What meant Chriſt by riſing? was it riſing in the grave, or out of the grave? Certainly out of the grave. VVill you have our witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes? Two Angels, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.5. <hi>Say unto theſe women, Why ſeek you the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving among the dead?</hi> If he be li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, he is not among the dead; therefore not in the grave, but out of the grave: It is the concluſion of the very Angels themſelves. Come to the next words following here, <hi>Go quickly, tell his Diſciples that he is riſen:</hi> Tell his Diſciples; then the Angels inſtructed them ſo, that they might have a faith that he was out of the grave, to the end they might
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:150077:44"/>perſwade the Diſciples, being now a foundation of the Articles of the Chriſtian Faith: But above all you will ſee it, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.6. He renders the words of Chriſt thus, <hi>He is not here, but he is riſen. But,</hi> that is a particle adverſitive, alwayes imply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a contradiction from the former; as if he ſhould ſay, ſuch a one is not dead, but alive; if therefore alive, not dead. Chriſt ſaith of his body, <hi>I am not ſpirit, but fleſh;</hi> fleſh there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, not ſpirit. Thus in all it is a contradiction in adjuncts: Therefore the truth is, this is an impoſſibility that the body of Chriſt can be in two places at once, which is the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion drawn from thence. Now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, I had not inſiſted ſo much upon this, except it had been;</p>
            <p>Firſt, that it was ſo full in my way, that I could not paſſe by it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe of the jealouſie of theſe times, wherein it is ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted that divers of the Eccleſiaſticks
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:150077:45"/>are infected with this leaven, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther leproſie of Popery, to think that the body of Chriſt can be in divers places at once: Therefore now I ſhall crave leave to inlarge my ſelf, and the rather becauſe in thus ſaying, whoſoever they be they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy it.</p>
            <p>I am therefore now beloved, to prove it unto you not by teſtimonies and allegations onely, but to deliver unto you the heads as I may ſay, the form and the reaſons ſummarily of true Antiquitie in the Primitive Church, and that ſhall confirm un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us this our doctrine to have been not onely a Catholique truth, but to have had the degree of a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique faith in the Church of God for ſix hundred years together. Briefly then thus; thoſe holy Fathers taught firſt, that no creature can be in divers places at once: why? for that this to be in divers places at once, is the Prerogative of God himſelf.</p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:150077:45"/>
            <p>Secondly, they prove that the holy Ghoſt the third Perſon in the Trinity is God. Why? for that it was in divers Prophets at once: <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remiah</hi> in <hi>Jewry, Daniel</hi> when he was in <hi>Babylon, Ezekiel</hi> in <hi>Cabar;</hi> and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo after that when he was in divers Apoſtles at once, they being diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed into divers Regions of the world.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, they prove that the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels are not Gods. Why? Becauſe Angels cannot be in divers places at once.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, they prove that no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, no bodily ſubſtance can be in divers places at once. Why? For that it is one body, and to be here and there in one inſtant, were to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide it ſelf from it ſelf; that it were two and one, and not one, are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, that we may omit divers others, they prove that the Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity is thus diſtinguiſhed from the Divinity, becauſe the Deity, the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:150077:46"/>nature that being in Heaven is in Earth, and every where elſe; but the humane nature if it be in Heaven, it is not on Earth, if on Earth it is not in Heaven. Thus theſe holy Fathers: You have their doctrine of truth. Now that it may appear unto you that this doctrine of truth was alſo a doctrine of faith, and that by two reaſons:</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe by theſe <hi>for's</hi> which are anſwerable to this <hi>for</hi> of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel here, they urged them againſt the Hereticks of their times, ſuch were the <hi>Marcionites,</hi> the <hi>Manichees,</hi> the <hi>Neucomitans,</hi> and ſuch like.</p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe they did this to this end that they might confirm unto all the world the doctrine of the Deity, to know that this is a Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative belonging to God alone; and ſecondly, for the preſervation of the true nature of the manhood of Chriſt; for whereas the <hi>Manichees</hi> might ſay that the body of Chriſt
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:150077:46"/>was in the Moon and the Deity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; <hi>fieri non poteſt,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtin,</hi> it cannot be; for by this means you will not make it a true body of Chriſt. I will conclude, and it ſhall be in the words of an holy Father that lived ſix hundred years after Chriſt, <hi>Vigilius</hi> by name, who ſaith thus, <hi>Humanitas Chriſti ſi in terra tunc non in coelo, &amp;c.</hi> The Humanity of Chriſt if it be on Earth, then cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly it is not in Heaven, if in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven bodily, then certainly not on earth. Was this his private opinion onely? No; <hi>Haec eſt Confeſsio Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholica quam, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the Confeſſion, a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique confeſſion, ſaith he, which the Apoſtles have delivered, the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs of Chriſt have confirmed, and now all the faithful in Chriſt do pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to this day. Beloved, this <hi>Vigilius</hi> was Biſhop of <hi>Trent,</hi> and he hath delivered unto us a confeſſion as contrary unto the laſt Councel of
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:150077:47"/>
               <hi>Trent,</hi> as yea and nay, truth and fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, Antiquity and Novelty; ſo that if the Primitive Church of Chriſt was the Catholique Church, certainly the now Romiſh church it is a ſtep-dame and degenerate. If the Primitive doctrine was a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique faith, and a legitimate childe, then the now doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> it is a baſtard-brat.</p>
            <p>Now then beloved, I have deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered unto you the points concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Logical part, wherein if I have been too obſcure, if that Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick part be too obſcure for ſome, I may make amends in the Hiſtorical, where I ſhall not make it ſo plain to your brains, as to your ſenſes. <hi>He is not here, for, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Hiſtorical part will offer unto you 3 obſervations concerning this doctrine of Chriſts Reſurrection; the firſt is,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That it is a truth moſt evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:150077:47"/>2. It is a truth Omnipotent.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is a truth Trimphant.</p>
            <p>For Chriſt after his Reſurrection manifeſted himſelf unto all men, all kinds of men that heard him Preach: he manifeſted himſelf to two, to twelve, to five hundred at once; to Saint <hi>Paul</hi> after his Aſcenſion into Heaven, here is all the eye-ſight: to other ſenſes; he manifeſted himſelf to his Apoſtles by feeling and hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling his body; here are three ſenſes. Now beloved, why ſhould not this be a foundation of truth to know and diſcern, to build our faith upon theſe things? The Apoſtl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aint <hi>John</hi> tells us that it ought to be ſo, for ſaith he, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.1. <hi>That which you have heard, that which you have ſeen, that which your hands have handled, that we declare unto you, &amp;c.</hi> He laies the faith of Chriſt on this founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, hearing, ſeeing, handling. Here again I am juſtly occaſioned to deal with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> by this
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:150077:48"/>light to diſpel the darkneſſe thereof, that their great infatuation concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the body of Chriſt; they ſay he is in the Sacrament in theſe three o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions: Firſt, he is here, ſay they, and yet his body is inviſible. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, it is here impalpable: And laſtly, 'tis in Heaven both viſible and palpable. It is here inviſible, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palpable, and yet it is in Heaven both viſible and palpable; three monſters which are now to be expulſed, not by the ſtrength of my wit, but by the authority of this Angel here ſpeaking from Chriſt, here ſpoken of, from t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Church of Chriſt, their whole voice for a general union for this; the Angel in the next words, even in this Text, this verſe, he ſaith unto the women, <hi>Come and ſee, Come and ſee where they laid the Lord.</hi> I ſay he is not here, I will prove it unto you, demonſtrate it unto your ſight, let your ſight be Judge; the arbitration of your ſight ſhall ſatisfie
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:150077:48"/>you: <hi>Come and ſee, he is not here; though they laid him here, he is not here;</hi> here is the argument of the Angel: But here they will tell us he paſſed by men out of company to avoid danger, and they ſaw him not. This is truth, but this is not all the truth; for the reaſon why they ſaw him not, it was becauſe their eyes were held that they could not ſee. How many of you now ſee this Pulpit? and yet wink with your eyes, you cannot ſee it. Is this Pulpit ere the leſſe viſible, becauſe you do not ſee it? When mens eyes are held, they cannot ſee, Chriſts body not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding was viſible ſtill to be ſeen. And now to confirm this that I have ſaid unto you, St. <hi>John</hi> himſelf ſhall make it good. <hi>There was one of the Diſciples</hi> (ſaith he <hi>John</hi> 20. and he ſpeaks of himſelf) the other Diſciple he looked into the ſepulchre, and he ſaw the linnen clothes, he ſaw not Chriſt there pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent;
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:150077:49"/>and what doth he but reſolve and beleeve that he was riſen out of the grave? And indeed it had been a mockery of theſe women, for the Angel, if their eyes being held, to bid them to ſee without their ſight. Therefore you have the firſt point concerning this ſenſe of Seeing ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently demonſtrated unto you. Come to our Saviour Chriſt: As the Angel ſaid to the woman, <hi>Come and ſee;</hi> ſo Chriſt he ſaid to his Diſciples, <hi>Come and feel, feel, I am I, this body is mine, feel my body, ſearch the wounds, &amp;c.</hi> So that now Chriſt makes this truth even palpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble unto them, that they may have their faith from the vertue of their own fingers. This is the doctrine of Chriſt, the body of Chriſt is pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pably to be ſeen; Come unto our faith, the Councel of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> one of the firſt Councels in the Chriſtian world, for the humane nature of Chriſt reſolves thus; <hi>Corpus Chriſti
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:150077:49"/>eſt &amp; viſibile &amp; palpabile ubicunque fuerit.</hi> The body of Chriſt it is viſible and tractable whereſoever it is; therefore may we come now to our reſolution, and conclude, that the body of Chriſt in the Sacrament of the Maſſe, you ſay it is inviſible, I ſay then it is not the body of Chriſt: Do you ſay it is impalpable? it is not the body of Chriſt. Do you ſay alſo it is both viſible and inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble? I return to the Fathers, and they ſay thus: This is, ſay they, ſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh. Why? you may as well ſay that the ſame body of Chriſt can be finite and infinite, it can be created and not created at once, which the diſtinction of places can never recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile.</p>
            <p>Oh, but ſay they unto us, this is natural reaſon, this is reaſoning like Ethnicks and Pagans. Nay, we have the Authority, which is the Authority of the Catholick Church, we have the Authority Angelical,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:150077:50"/>we have not onely the Authority E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelical, but of Chriſt himſelf. <hi>He is not here, &amp;c.</hi> Thus I have ſhewn that he is palpable whereſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he be: Now the evidence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus plain, let us aſcend a little higher, to know, that what if ſome ſhould ſay, that notwithſtanding theſe evidences, I doubt whether this doctrine be true or no, that Chriſt is riſen? Our Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> hath anſwered this argument long ago, when he ſaid thus; <hi>If that Chriſt be not riſen, we are falſe witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes:</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, a thing moſt incredible, for they which were with our Lord and Saviour, and ſaw, and heard, and felt him, were alwayes ready to lay down their lives for Chriſt, and for this very Article, <hi>he is riſen.</hi> There Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeak for himſelf; <hi>If Chriſt be not riſen, what ſhould it advantage me that I fought with beaſts at Epheſus after the manner of men, to endanger my life for</hi>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:150077:50"/>this Article, <hi>Chriſt is riſen?</hi> and this was that <hi>Paul</hi> that could ſay of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. <hi>That among all thoſe many troubles and afflictions for this profeſsion,</hi> In carcere, &amp;c. <hi>I was in death often, oftentimes left for dead, ſtoned and perſecuted,</hi> ſo manifold a Martyr was this one Saint <hi>Paul.</hi> He ſpeaks alſo of the reſt of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>We are in jeopardy eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day,</hi> every day in jeopardy, even for this Article, and this truth that <hi>Chriſt is riſen</hi> he ſtands upon, in that 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. Well then beloved, for the eſtabliſhing of our Chriſtian faith in this one point, certainly theſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles of Chriſt had been moſt ſhameleſſe, if they had publiſhed to all that which they ſaw not; moſt faithleſſe, if they had not believed that which they all ſaw; moſt heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, if they had not ventured their lives for the profeſſion of that, the reſurrection of Chriſt from the dead, by vertue whereof their bodies
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:150077:51"/>ſhould alſo be reſerved to eternal life; and moſt fooliſh alſo, if they ſhould have ſpent their bloud for that they believed not, they having thus ſeen, thus heard, thus belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, thus Preached, thus dying and ſuffering death, they may be eyes, and have been to the Chriſtian world, to ſee by their faith; and ſo I perſwade my ſelf of you all that are here preſent, to give faith unto this Article of the reſurrection of Chriſt from death; and therefore I am authoriſed to give unto you the benediction which Chriſt gave unto ſuch as you, ſaying, <hi>Bleſſed are they that ſee not, and yet believe;</hi> and ſo Bleſſed be you.</p>
            <p>Now you have heard the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, this is an evident truth, we have not yet heard the power of it, but that is in the next part, wherein I ſaid that this is a truth which is Omnipotent, an Omnipotent truth, look to our Text; I, but ſaith the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:150077:51"/>Evangeliſt, <hi>He is riſen;</hi> he doth not ſay <hi>Agarthes,</hi> he is raiſed, but he is riſen, and becauſe it was he that rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed himſelf from the dead: It is he that ſaid, <hi>I have power to lay down my life, and to take it up again;</hi> lay down my life by dying, to take it up again by riſing: as eaſie to take it up as to lay it down, to lay down my life as man, to take it up again as God. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as he ſaid of the ſame body to the Jews, <hi>Deſtroy you this Temple, I will raiſe it up in three dayes.</hi> Deſtroy it, then its deſtructive; but raiſe it up in three dayes, there's his God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head. Thus he ſpake once, let us put them together, God and Man, Man and God. How prove we it? The Apoſtle proves it, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.1. of Chriſt, thus, he was declared migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily to be the Son of God by his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection from the dead. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon Saint <hi>Auſtin,</hi> Oh <hi>miraculum miraculorum!</hi> This is a miracle of miracles, the Sun of all Suns, never
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:150077:52"/>the like, that one dead ſhould raiſe himſelf from the dead; this could not be man, but God; it muſt needs be as the Apoſtle to the <hi>Coloſsians, The Godhead dwelling in him bodily which raiſed himſelf from the dead:</hi> now beloved, from hence it muſt follow, that it was impoſſible for him to be detained in the grave; and S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. it was impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for Chriſt to be detained in the pangs of death; it is a word taken from women travailing in child, when the throwes and pangs are up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her ſhe cannot contain her bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, it muſt go out. Well ſaid <hi>Chryſologus</hi> of this burden, <hi>Concepit mortuum &amp; peperit vivum:</hi> Here is a difference then between this womb and all the reſt of the world, concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving dead, and bringing forth alive; and indeed ſo it muſt needs bee when Omnipotency is the Midwife, as it was with <hi>Jonas,</hi> a type of Chriſt, ſwallowed up of the Whale, the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:150077:52"/>could not digeſt it, it muſt be caſt out. Of what uſe muſt this be to us? the ſame power that raiſed him from death to life, the ſame power will give us reſurrection to life ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, even our bodies. So the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. <hi>He will change our vile bodies, and make them like unto his glorious body.</hi> So much for the ſecond point, that I call it an Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent truth.</p>
            <p>The next is, that it is alſo a trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant truth; there are two trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phings of Chriſt that we read of in Scripture, and they are admirable; the one is of his Paſſion, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther not of his, but of the general Reſurrection; the one is an Introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the other; of his Paſſion thus, <hi>Col.</hi> 2. <hi>He having ſpoiled princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palities and powers, made a ſhew of them openly, and triumphed over them on the Croſs.</hi> Here is his triumph, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a conquerour over principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities and powers; he made a ſhew of
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:150077:53"/>them openly, he ſpoiled them, there's the conquering; ſold them openly, there's the preparation for the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph of the people, and to look upon all as a conquerour, there's his triumph; this triumph thus ſpokes of it hath alluſion unto the triumphs of the world, and eſpecially that of the Romane State, wherein there was firſt preſented a multitude of Trumpeters, ſounding out the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, and reſounding; then came in chariots of ſpoils, ſpoils of armour, ſpoils of riches; the conquerour he ſits in the midſt looking back unto thoſe noble ſlaves that came be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, their wives, their children, and all their hands bound about them. I will paſſe no farther in the ſtory, enough for application. Now I beſeech you extend your mind as much as you can that we may behold at leaſt ſome glimpſe of this great victory of our Saviour Chriſt and of his conqueſt. Here now, where was
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:150077:53"/>his ſight of Majeſty? he was now gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving up the ghoſt upon the Croſſe, and behold a triumph, why God and Man the Deity never forſook the Manhood, no not in his death; the vertue of his death was the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifying of the Devil and all his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: And now I come to the ſlaves of this triumph, the principalities and powers, namely, the greateſt powers that can be conceived in creatures; and who ſhould deal with them but he that is above all power, Chriſt our Saviour? What doth he ſpoil them of? of all their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, be they never ſo miſchievous; he ſpoils them of all their wiles, and prevents them they can do nothing, never any thing to the prejudice of the children of God regenerate, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any thing that ſhall work to his overthrow: This is that ſpoil, and he leads them, as it is here in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Text, open in view, he goes not out of ſight; So that this point is
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:150077:54"/>contemplative; here is no Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bims or Seraphims, Angels or Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angels, but whatſoever can be ſeen in the world by the mortal eyes, that was viſibly performed by Chriſt. Thus much for that ſecond triumph; and ſo it ſhall be in the general reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. <hi>Oh death, where is thy ſting? Oh Hell, or Grave, where is thy victory? The ſting of death is ſin, and the ſtrength of ſin is the law; but thanks be to God who hath given us victory through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; Thanks be to God that he hath given us victory in Chriſt our Lord.</hi> Now mark I beſeech you the manifold circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of this victory in the day of the reſurrection of the holy Saints and Martyrs. What will become of the Law? the Law of God it ſhall be cancelled; no more Law here, and the Law it is the ſtrength of ſin; for if there were no law, there were no tranſgreſſion, the law being taken away, there is no more ſin; and as for
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:150077:54"/>ſins paſt, they are either pardoned or puniſhed in the day of the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Well then, but ſin it is the ſting of death, what becomes of death? Death it is ſwallowed up in victory: Death's dead, no more giving up of the ghoſt. Come to the Grave; Grave where is thy victory? When the Trumpets ſound, and the Angel gives his voice, <hi>ariſe ye dead, and come unto Judgement,</hi> they come out of their Graves, the Graves are empty. But the great enemies are Hell and the Devil: Hell where's thy victory? The conqueſt being before, as you heard, concerning the paſſage of the ſouls of men, the gates of Hell are ſhut up, no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe nor egreſſe, but all is ſhut, they are all detained, as the Apoſtle ſaith, in the chains of darkneſſe and torments for ever. And this is our victory; <hi>Thanks be to God that hath given us victory in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord, Amen.</hi> Thus have I ended
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:150077:55"/>the Hiſtorical point, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd us in the evidence of this truth, that you have heard that he is riſen, and of the power thereof: All this while we have not learned the cauſes of this reſurrection, that belongs to the third part which I ſaid was Analogical, and this hath three conſiderations:</p>
            <p>The firſt is this; Chriſt here in the Text is to be conſidered, in the firſt place, as the general cauſe of the Reſurrection of the world of men.</p>
            <p>The ſecond conſideration is this, That he in this Text is the ſpecial cauſe of the reſurrection of all the ſouls everlaſtingly bleſſed.</p>
            <p>The third conſideration of him is, as he is riſen as an example, That it is poſſible there may be a reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the death of the body. Firſt, the reſurrection of Chriſt teacheth us a certainty of reſurrection, that he is the ſpecial effectual cauſe of the reſurrection to life everlaſting unto
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:150077:55"/>the ſons of God that ſhew the actions of the reſurrection of Chriſt. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, there is a generality or uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſality of Reſurrection. Thirdly, the poſſibility of the bodies reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction unto life. To begin with the univerſality, all muſt riſe again; by whom? by whoſe power? why? by Chriſts, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.6. <hi>As by the ſin of the firſt Adam death came upon all men, ſo by Chriſt the Reſurrection from the dead:</hi> all men, all manner of men, all men dying, all men riſing, all the ſons of men. We have an Apoſtle for it: <hi>All men,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. <hi>All men muſt dye, all men muſt appear before the Tribunal Seat of Chriſt, and give an account of all things they did in this life, be it good or bad.</hi> Here's good and bad, all men. This was believed by the Jews before Chriſt came; ſo the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Peter, Acts</hi> 2. ſhews unto us, That they believed the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection from the dead. They
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:150077:56"/>believed the Prophet <hi>Daniel,</hi> that <hi>they ſhould riſe, the juſt and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, Dan.</hi> 12. Here's all that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets prophecy, <hi>ſome to honour, and ſome to ſhame;</hi> here's either honour, or ſhame: A ſhame there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it will be unto us, beloved, if we do not believe that which they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved. That we having before us not a prophecie which Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith is a dark light; they believed in a dark light, in a light in a dark place, and we have the very Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine of the Goſpel to inſtruct us: But what inſtruction do we learn from this univerſality? It com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends unto us the general Juſtice of God, that as he will be both vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cative and remunerative to the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of men, they muſt riſe again; vindicative, to puniſh wicked men, and remunerative, to reward the godly, even in their bodies. Our reaſon; That as the body hath been an inſtrument unto the ſoul for acting
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:150077:56"/>either good or evil, ſo they ſhould be co-partners together in weal or woe. We ſee the ſame ſhadowed in the Parable, the finger of the poor man in Heaven, and the tongue of the rich man in Hell, yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding it muſt be the ſame bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: and as <hi>Job</hi> ſaid of his eyes, <hi>I know that my Redeemer liveth, and I ſhall ſee him with theſe eyes, and no other.</hi> The ſame eyes; For belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, how ſhould it conſiſt with the Juſtice of God, that one body ſhould glutton, gormandiſe and ſwell with exceſſe, and wallow in ſenſual plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and there ſhould be another body put upon him that ſhould cry out, <hi>I am tormented in theſe flames?</hi> Or for the godly, as for example, Saint <hi>Stephen,</hi> whoſe name ſignifies a Crown, that he ſhould ſuffer Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome for this truth we are now proving, the Reſurrection, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards another body be given unto him, which ſhould be clothed with
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:150077:57"/>bleſſedneſſe, which is called the Crown of Righteouſneſs? No, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, it is a certain and an infallible truth, that it muſt be diſpoſed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Juſtice of God. There's a ſtatute for it, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.9. <hi>Statutum eſt, &amp;c.</hi> It is appointed and ſtatuted for all men to dye, and after death comes Judgment; all men firſt to dye, and then comes Judgment, Judgment as ſure as death. Here is matter of horrour, and matter of comfort; horrour to the wicked, that when that great and general Goal-delivery comes, it ſhall be as it is ſometimes at the Aſſiſes; there are two men in priſon, and one hath either got his pardon, or elſe he is innocent, that none can impeach him; and he ſaith to his fellows, I am going before the Judge for deliverance out of priſon. Another he hath Guilty branded in his forehead, and he cryes, I am go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before the Judge, but it is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive my condemnation, and to be
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:150077:57"/>delivered over to execution: So ſhall it be in the end of time, and in this general Reſurrection; Then as it is in the <hi>Apocalypſe,</hi> the wicked that ſhould appear before the Judge, ſhall cry to the rocks to cover them, and the mountains to fall upon them, to deliver them from the wrath of the Lamb, and yet to them he is a Tyger; looking upon their guilti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and deſperation, they call and cry for impoſſibilities, rocks to hide them from the Judge of all Judges, and hills to cover them from the God of all Gods. But as for the godly, they come and ſay, <hi>Now is our Redemption at hand;</hi> for that which concerns redemption and comfort it belongs to them. The next conſideration is the neceſſity of the reſurrection. Now hear how neceſſary this reſurrection is. We read of many benefits in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture of God concerning all men by vertue of Chriſts birth, his life,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:150077:58"/>his merits, his preaching, his paſſion, his dying. But what if there were no Reſurrection? The Apoſtle tells us, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. <hi>Then were our faith in vain.</hi> Our whole faith were vain, if there were not a reſurrection, we preach in vain: And indeed were there no reſurrection, though the birth of Chriſt were never ſo joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, the miracles that he wrought in the world never ſo miraculous, his promiſes for everlaſting life never ſo gracious, his work and price of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption never ſo meritorious, yet if there were no reſurrection, his birth, his life, his miracles, his paſſion, yea, his death it ſelf put together, the ſame ſtone that covered his corpſe, ſhould cover all thoſe ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar infinite benefits. But now he is riſen, this work of the reſurrection it is both the perfection and comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all the Articles that went before, ſo it is alſo the foundation of all the Articles that come after,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:150077:58"/>riſing, communion, ſitting at the right hand of God in glory: See the neceſſity of this reſurrection, and there is alſo the like neceſſity laid upon us, ſeeing this reſurrection is the vertue of our reſurrection: So the Apoſtle to the <hi>Coloſsians</hi> tells us, <hi>That Chriſt is the Head of the Church, and the firſt begotten of the dead.</hi> He muſt have the preeminence, he is the firſt begotten of the dead, for he aſcended firſt into Heaven, to take poſſeſſion, there's his preheminence; Happy are we if we can come after, as we may come, for he did not take poſſeſſion for himſelf alone, but as the head of the whole body, <hi>he is the firſt begotten among the dead.</hi> And this for the comfort of all; Be that inſeparable union between us and Chriſt known unto you, I do not ſay in our ſouls alone, but in our bodies alſo; for ſo the Apoſtle, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. <hi>We are fleſh of his fleſh, and bone of his bone.</hi> Oh beloved, when the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:150077:59"/>holy Fathers of the Primitive Church fell upon this Text, they were raviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with contemplations thereof; to think there was ſuch an individual union between Chriſt and them, even our bodies. And this union is more then if there were a reality of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration in body and body, by the vertue whereof he our head is riſen, that we may riſe again; and ſooner ſhall Chriſt ſuffer his fleſh to be torn from his body, then that any one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate Chriſtian man ſhall be ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from him in the reſurrection to eternal glory. Thus ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4. <hi>They ſhall be alwayes with him.</hi> Now then thus you ſee as in the reſurrection of Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, ſo in our reſurrection, although that all our joy in the birth of Chriſt, all our ſaith in the promiſes of Chriſt, and in the vertue of his death, and all our hope of glory to come, it is riſen from theſe words of my Text, by the vertue of this, <hi>He is
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:150077:59"/>riſen.</hi> This is the neceſſity, which is the ſecond conſideration I ſpake of; and now beloved, methinks I hear the voices of prophane men that ſay, What do you tell us of the reſurrection, of the univerſality, the happineſſe or neceſſity of Chriſts reſurrection, before you can ſhew unto us the poſſibility thereof? This is the next point which I am to han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle unto you, That it is poſſible that all ſhall riſe again. I prove it from the Text, there's a poſſibility, and thus it ſtands, <hi>He is riſen;</hi> if one man be riſen from the dead, its poſſible for another that's dead to riſe again. Here's the argument, and yet behold there are two adverſaries againſt this argument. The one is imaginary, and denyeth the conſequence; the other is peremptory and pernicious, and denies the antecedent. The conſequence is this, <hi>ergo</hi> another man may riſe again. The imaginary man that reads that Text, <hi>Thou wilt not
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:150077:60"/>ſuffer thine holy One to ſee corruption,</hi> reaſons in his fancy not peremptori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, not certainly, why there is diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt Chriſts riſing and a Chriſtian mans, for Chriſt he is that <hi>holy One without ſin;</hi> We ſinners, for theſe reaſons: His body felt no cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, our bodies even putrified unto corruption it ſelf. He the holy One, he could hallow his own grave, ſo cannot we, for we are corrupt. Theſe are his fancies; now peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture you may think they deſerve no anſwer; not much indeed, and yet the anſwer whatſoever it ſhall be, I hope it ſhall be pertinent and not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable.</p>
            <p>To the firſt therefore thus; He it is true had no ſin, he was innocent, yea, innocency it ſelf. Now every one of us, whoſoever they be that are in the world, that will ſay they are no ſinners, and have no ſin, the Apoſtle Saint <hi>John</hi> will give him the lye, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1. <hi>There is no truth is
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:150077:60"/>him.</hi> He hath no part in Chriſts reſurrection, no affinity with him, and by nature we are born aliens from him: So to conſider that he being crucified of men moſt wickedly, deſperately, cruelly, blaſphemouſly handled of ſinners, any natural man would think now that he is riſen, <hi>Theanthropos,</hi> God and man, He ſhould abhor all men, and loath the ſight of all ſinners, and become <hi>Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anthropos.</hi> But behold and marvel, how he recollects himſelf in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of ſinners immediately after his reſurrection. Saint <hi>Mark chap.</hi> 16. tells us, <hi>That Chriſt appeared firſt to Mary Magdalene.</hi> Note, as much as if he ſhould have ſaid, he appeared firſt of all unto one that had been a moſt notorious ſinner, ſhe out of whom he had caſt ſeven Devils, this deſerves a Marginal Note; and ſpeaks unto her in a mild compella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Mary,</hi> that's for her. The Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples of Chriſt they forſook him,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:150077:61"/>and turned apoſtates from Chriſt; but did Chriſt forſake them? No: In the tenth verſe of this Chapter he ſaith unto them, <hi>Go and tell them;</hi> yea, they were more then forſakers, for among the Diſciples there was one <hi>Peter,</hi> he that had vowed above all the reſt not to deny Chriſt, yet he diſclaimed and diſavowed him; what's become of him? This Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger of Chriſt, this Angel ſaith, <hi>Go and tell the Diſciples,</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> by name, leſt he might be miſt. But what ſhall we ſay for <hi>Thomas?</hi> meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage upon meſſage comes unto him, <hi>We have ſeen him, he is riſen:</hi> Chriſt comes and gives his bleſſing to all his Diſciples, ſaying, <hi>Peace be unto you;</hi> cryes, <hi>Thomas, Thomas, come and feel and believe.</hi> Beloved, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold here the mirrour of all merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe in our Saviour Chriſt. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what Chriſt is: An Angel tells us he was therefore called a Saviour, becauſe <hi>he ſhould ſave his people from
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:150077:61"/>their ſins;</hi> this was in his Paſſion; <hi>he dyed for our ſins, and roſe again for our juſtification:</hi> So in his Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But now he is above all princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palities and powers, after his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of theſe principalities and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, when he <hi>led Captivity Captive,</hi> and will he now vouchſafe pardon unto ſinners? It is his profeſſion, <hi>If any man ſin, we have an Advocate with the Father, Jeſus Chriſt the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and he is the propitiation for our ſins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next Exception that was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to the conſequence, was this; That he was the holy One that ſaw no corruption, but we are corrupt and putrified; the beſt of us all with lying but four dayes in the grave, will be little better then <hi>Lazarus,</hi> rotten and ſtinking. Yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding remember that <hi>Lazarus</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dead, what Chriſt ſaid to his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples, <hi>Our brother Lazarus is aſleep, let us go and wake him.</hi> So it is with
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:150077:62"/>all our corpſes, though they be turned into duſt. Lend me your attenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; Let us all go to <hi>Golgotha,</hi> the place of dead mens skuls; look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them with the eye of faith, as thoſe that will riſe in the reſurrection among the juſt. But if there be any ſuch here, that Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks of, ſaying, <hi>In the laſt dayes there ſhall come ſcoffers, denying the reſurrection,</hi> we may deal with theſe faithleſs as Chriſt with the Fidlers, turn them out of our company, that we have no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation with them: So that Chriſt here being the holy One, and we his members, we ſhall in the end be holy ones with Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The laſt is the hallowing of our Graves; and the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>He is the firſt-fruits of them that ſleep.</hi> Chriſt riſen, and in Heaven, he is there but the firſt-fruits of the dead in behalf of us. <hi>The firſt-fruits of them that ſleep:</hi> Alluding to that in the old Law, where the Prieſts were to
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:150077:62"/>take ſheaves out of the field before they were ripe, and to offer them up to God, and by oblation of thoſe ſheaves all the field of Corn was ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified to the people: So it is here, Chriſt is the firſt-fruits, whereſoever mans body be, be it in the ditch, or on the dunghill, be it in the mawes of birds or beaſts, all our bodies through him are ſanctified unto God. So having done with this, I come to the Hereticallizer, who denies all poſſibility of reſurrection, the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent. He will ſtand upon na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural reaſon: Now there is two wayes, if I were to deal with a Jew I would eaſily confute him; If a Jew, I would ſtand upon the principles of our Saviour Chriſt, in his anſwer to the Sadduces; <hi>You erre, not knowing Scriptures, nor the power of God.</hi> The Scripture tells you you ſhall riſe, and where's the power that's in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures? Alſo there's <hi>Moſes</hi> leprous hand, and preſently healed; there's
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:150077:63"/>
               <hi>Aarons</hi> rod, dry, yet preſently budded and bloſſomed; <hi>Sarah</hi> being barren, ſhortly after bears a child; <hi>Jonah</hi> three dayes and three nights in the whales belly &amp; yet riſeth again. <hi>Eze.</hi> 37. There were dry bones, and yet bones creep unto bones, ſinews creep unto thoſe bones, and knit them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and fleſh comes and knits thoſe ſinews, and then God puts life, and then they become men. But we are to deal with the man that is meerly natural, and ſtands altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon his own reaſon, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thus: If he will take the pains to go into <hi>Arabia,</hi> there he may hear of the Phoenix, that conſumes it ſelf in the fire, and another riſeth out of thoſe aſhes. But that's too far: Come neerer hand, to the Bombyx, the Silk-worm, he dyes, and out of his duſt comes a Fly. Theſe are yet remote; will you have them domeſtical? in our own Land we ſhall finde the like: In ſome places
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:150077:63"/>the Bees, the Flyes, the Waſps are produced out of the Hides of Beaſts of divers kinds: But except I ſee a natural reaſon I will not believe it. Perhaps you will ſay with <hi>Thomas, I will not believe, unleſſe I ſee it and feel it.</hi> Well, ſeeing theſe will not ſerve thy turn, what ſhall I do unto thee? Even as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſent the Sluggard to the Ant to labour, ſo muſt I thee. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> he ſends a Naturaliſt or natural Fool to learn of a little ſeed of Corn the reſurrection from the dead; <hi>Thou fool, when thou ſoweſt, the ſeed lives not before it dyes: and yet you may ſee it live, you may ſee it dye, after it is turned to duſt, it lives again:</hi> And by this he foolifies all the generation of Philoſophers and Infidels; and as we ſay, <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres,</hi> which withſtood <hi>Moſes</hi> by falſe miracles, were conquered by one true miracle of Lice; So all theſe are confounded in this one ſeed; and even here is the finger of God, and as much in this
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:150077:64"/>as ever it was in that, to the confuſion of thoſe that withſtand it. Now beloved, that you have heard all theſe points opened, there remains the fourth, and that's the Moral point. About which I had ſtudied not a little, but foreſeeing I ſhould treſpaſſe upon your patience, I have contracted my ſelf into ſome few In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions concerning the Moral part; and the firſt is this:</p>
            <p>That the Reſurrection of Chriſt requires of every Chriſtian a confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of holineſſe of life; and the Apoſtle will make it good, for thus he ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. <hi>That as Chriſt roſe again, ſo ſhould we walk in newneſs of life:</hi> So that newneſſe of life is a conformity to the Reſurrection of Chriſt. I ſpeak of this newneſſe of life the rather, becauſe it is a reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in it ſelf. So Saint <hi>John, Apoc.</hi> 20. <hi>Thoſe that are partakers of the firſt reſurrection,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ſhall never fall into the ſecond death.</hi> By the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:150077:64"/>firſt Reſurrection, newneſſe of life, we are made partakers of the ſecond reſurrection; and from hence may ariſe divers inſtructions. The firſt ſhall be this; That all Chriſtian ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues they take their riſing from the doctrine of the reſurrection unto eternal life, that comprehends all vertues that can be imagined, <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 1. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> gives a direction <hi>that we ſhould live ſoberly, juſtly, holily in this preſent world.</hi> Here's a Triplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive vertue which contains all others; we muſt <hi>live ſoberly,</hi> this requires temperance and ſobriety, &amp;c. <hi>juſtly,</hi> that extends to all relation we have to Superiours or Governours; and the other is <hi>holineſſe,</hi> which brings upon us all the obligations that we have concerning God and his worſhip in this preſent world: What follows? <hi>looking for the hope of the mighty God, and of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Beloved, how ſhould this raviſh the hearts of men to <hi>live ſoberly, juſtly and holily
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:150077:65"/>in this preſent world?</hi> When as the true Chriſtian regenerate may ſay with the holy Apoſtle, that he hath an expectation, an hope, a looking for the appearance, the bleſſed ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, the glorious appearance of God, a mighty God, and of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt. Here you ſee that our ſalvation depends upon theſe triplicite vertues. Again, Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. ſaith thus, <hi>there are the three, Faith, Hope, and Charity.</hi> What have theſe to do with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection? Certainly the doctrine of the reſurrection is made ſure by theſe: Therefore for Faith firſt, be it known unto you, I ſpeak of a living faith, not of a dead faith, void of repentance and newneſſe of life. This is a dead faith which he calls a Devilliſh faith; but I ſpeak of that faith which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> affirms to work by love: Of this faith our Saviour Chriſt ſaith, <hi>He that believeth in me, though he dye, yet ſhall be live;</hi>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:150077:65"/>Here is living of dying. This is a reſurrection, and he that believes this, doth believe he ſhall riſe. The next to Faith is Charity; of this St. <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>We know we are tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from death to life, becauſe we love the brethren.</hi> Therefore love the brethren, becauſe we ſhall be preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from death to life. Now come to open it, and that in the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, where it is ſaid, The people of God were tormented, racked, ſuffered all manner of perſecution, becauſe they looked for a better re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, that is, the reſurrection of the body to be better then all the torments and afflictions the world could lay upon them. Surely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, we can look for no better re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection then theſe holy men did that ſuffered for the reſurrection; but we may better look for it then they, they looked upon it with dim eyes, and they believed, but we have open eyes, we may ſee it by moſt evident
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:150077:66"/>demonſtrations; they never ſaw Chriſt raiſed from the dead, reigning in Majeſty, in Eternity and Glory; this doctrine are we made ſenſible of. Now therefore ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>If we ſuffer with him, we ſhall alſo be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified with him.</hi> So much for our Hope.</p>
            <p>The ſecond point is this: That our firſt reſurrection requires that our worſhip and ſervice unto God in holineſſe be as well performed in body as in ſoul. Thus the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Glorifie God in your bodies and ſouls, you are bought with a price;</hi> Glorifie God with your bodies; and yet behold greater then theſe: Let every man ſay unto himſelf, I am created by God both body and ſoul, <hi>Ergo,</hi> I will glorifie him in both: But ſince I have treſpaſſed againſt my God, and thereby loſt both body and ſoul; Therefore, thirdly, there comes a Redeemer unto me, and he ſuffers for me ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:150077:66"/>and pangs both in body and ſoul; therefore by this ſuffering he hath freed me from everlaſting death and torments both of body and ſoul. This is not all, but beſides this, the price ſpoken of here which is the price of redemption, is alſo a price purchaſing of glory in the Heavens for my body and ſoul, and therefore let them that have bodies and ſouls know that there is a duty lies upon them to glorifie God in their lives both in their bodies and ſouls. The next point is this; That the ſinful body hath a dead ſoul; every ſinful body wallowing in ſin hath a dead ſoul: So we read, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.5. The woman living in pleaſure, ſhe was dead though ſhe lived. Again, the Biſhop of <hi>Sardis,</hi> a wicked Biſhop, but yet a Biſhop, I am ſure a Biſhop; <hi>Thou haſt a name that thou liveſt, but thou art dead.</hi> Our Saviour Chriſt ſaid unto the ſurvivers of thoſe that were dead, Survivers unto
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:150077:67"/>them, and go and attend their Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and Herſe; <hi>Go,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>let the dead in ſins bury their dead:</hi> So you ſee that theſe wicked ones they have but the carkaſſe of Chriſtians. And as nothing is more ugly and odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in the ſight of man then the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaſſe of man; ſo there is nothing more deteſtable in the ſight of God then a wicked, obſtinate and impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſinner. Again, the mortified body hath a living ſoul; It is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary that this be preached unto all the world, becauſe moſt of the world have forgot themſelves. And the principal part of Chriſtianity conſiſts in this mortification and ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. We all live in ſins, doſt thou live in actual ſin, bodily ſin? thou art dead, if thou be not mortified in them. <hi>Give up your bodies a living ſacrifice,</hi> that is, mortification; <hi>let not ſin reign in your mortal bodies.</hi> I will give you a pattern of S. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. <hi>But I chaſtiſe my
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:150077:67"/>body, and bring it into ſubjection;</hi> So then you ſee that this is a matter on which conſiſts eternal life. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle tells us, <hi>If you mortifie the luſts of the fleſh, you ſhall live, if not, you ſhall dye.</hi> Its a matter of life and death, which is to ſhew that thoſe that are mortified men have a living ſoul. Again, we muſt take heed of bodily and actual tranſgreſſions, for I muſt tell you that theſe acts of men done in their bodies, ſhall have reſurrection with them, even with their bodies: This is a profitable point, for God ſees all things before him, all things that have been or can be, he ſees them all in preſent, as it were in preſent, that's the infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his Science. Now then what ſaith the Apoſtle? <hi>We all muſt appear before the Tribunal-Seat of Chriſt, and every one ſhall give an account of thoſe things that are done in his fleſh;</hi> fleſhly body: So then whereas the Epicure ſings his Ballad, and the burthen of
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:150077:68"/>his Song is, <hi>Let us eat and drink, for to morrow we ſhall dye;</hi> yet death will come, and then we muſt give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of all our actions. So much for my Text.</p>
            <p>Becauſe I was told I ſhould make ſome application concerning the preſent occaſion, I do therefore ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe my ſelf and my ſpeech unto you Right Honourable, and to all your reverend Senate, and to all your Aſſociate Worthies: Firſt, we muſt give an acknowledgment unto God, and bleſſe his great goodneſſe, that hath ſo ſanctified the hearts of our Predeceſſors of former times to leave ſuch worthy and real Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies to the world of their piety and godly devotion; devotion both for the Church and Houſes of God, and charity unto the poor; theſe have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived their rewards, the full rewards of all their labours on Earth, in the Heavens, where they ſhall remain for ever in the higheſt Seat of Glory;
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:150077:68"/>they are now Canonized by God himſelf, and have left themſelves in their memories and examples for you and thoſe that ſhall be able to walk in their ſteps. The Roll that I have ſeen ſpeaks of wonderful bleſſed Foundations, of Hoſpitality for the relief of hundreds, and hundreds, and thouſands. It doth not need ſo much to put them here in your Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendar and Paper, for the comfort of men, but that their good examples might ſtir up others to the like du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of piety and charity, in reſpect of thoſe that are the Founders, all their names are regiſtred in the Book of Life for all Eternity.</p>
            <p>My Exhortation unto you muſt be, that you would enlarge your mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence both wayes, in duties of piety and charity, but eſpecially of charity, becauſe of the objects be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes, the Orphans, that have ſung joyfully and comfortably unto God by way of Thankſgiving. I
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:150077:69"/>ſhall not ſtand to reaſon with you, I ſhall onely apply thoſe things which are appliable unto the men of the world, as they are worldly men, and apply the promiſes of God unto them, as they are worldly, though the promiſes are all Heavenly, and ye with a recommendation to men as worldly men; for you look to have habitation here in the world, behold the poor, that you beſtow your cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity on, <hi>they ſhall bring you</hi> (you know the place of Scripture, I do but name the words) <hi>into eternal habitations.</hi> You labour for trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and the promiſe is, that you ſhall have treaſure in Heaven. Will you have bags for your treaſures? the Goſpel is, that theſe Orphans, and ſuch like, how mortal ſoever they may be, yet unto God they are bags, thoſe bags that will never wear out. Will you have a trade of life for the beſt advantage? then without all compariſon, it is charitable uſury; the
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:150077:69"/>promiſe is, <hi>You ſhall receive an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred fold,</hi> be the poor what they will of themſelves; the gift is to God, and to Chriſt, not ſo much un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, for be they wanderers in the world, as we ſay rogues ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, charity is not alwayes ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious without cauſe. What faith the Wiſe man to us, <hi>Caſt thy bread upon the waters, for after many dayes thou ſhalt find it with advantage;</hi> that thou giveſt unto ſuch a man, though unworthy: what ſaith <hi>Job? his loins ſhall bleſs thee;</hi> thou giveſt mortal things, and he gives immortal bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, his loins ſhall bleſſe thee. Whatſoever thou doſt to the poor, their loins, and their back, and their belly ſhall bleſſe thee, for it comes from God. But withal let us know and remember why it is that the Lord Jeſus Chriſt our Saviour would ſet down the tenure of ſalvation or damnation upon the giving or not giving unto the poor, it is, becauſe
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:150077:70"/>it is ſuch a work if rightly done, that proceeds from a true faith, and therefore God knows that it is a work that proceeds from true cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; and thoſe that do thus, and make conſcience of it, as giving it for Gods ſake indeed, and Chriſts ſake indeed, certainly they are Chriſts, and will walk according to the Precepts of Faith. And now I conclude with prayer, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And thus this Pillar, this reverend Father of the Church of God, this ſound Divine, as heretofore he hath aſſerted the truth of our Religion by his hand-writing againſt grand Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, and againſt all the Chaos of Antichriſts deviſes, as then by his pen, ſo now by his tongue, did vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate the Reſurrection, which is the Fundamental Article of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; for <hi>Reſurrectio à mortuis eſt fides Chriſtianorum,</hi> the reſurrection
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:150077:70"/>from the dead is the faith of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; and if you will know what fruit there is from Chriſts riſing from the dead, the third Preacher will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form you, and I ſhall uſe no other Introduction then his own. I will ſhew you that it agrees well with the reſurrection from the dead (for the mercy of God flowes from this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of our Saviour, for he dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for our ſins, and roſe that our ſouls might be ſaved) in that melting Sermon of his which was anchored upon that place in the <hi>Pſalms</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="sermon">
            <pb n="124" facs="tcp:150077:71"/>
            <head>A Sermon Preached by Doctor <hi>Potter</hi> Biſhop <hi>Carliſle,</hi> at the <hi>Spit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle</hi> on Tueſday in <hi>Eaſter</hi> week.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSALM 130.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>But there is mercy with thee, that thou maiſt be feared.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE words are an Appeal of the Princely Prophet <hi>David</hi> from the Throne of Juſtice to the Throne of Goodneſſe; and are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable in their Context and in
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:150077:71"/>their Text. Firſt, in their Context, and that three ſeveral wayes: Firſt, they muſt be conſidered in way of conſequence, as they follow the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer verſe: Firſt, he ſpeaks of the Judgment of God; <hi>If thou O Lord, ſhouldſt enter into Judgment, who could ſtand?</hi> And then he comes in with a diſcourſe of Mercy. And ſecondly, as in order, ſo he tempers Juſtice and Mercy together. Thirdly, as they are a cry of perplexity, he cries in the firſt verſe, complains in the ſecond verſe, fears in the third, and here he reſolves to ſet upon Mercy.</p>
            <p>The firſt point from the firſt of theſe is, That we can neither ſenſibly nor ſafely Preach mercy in forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſins, unleſſe as we do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint you with the Juſtice of God, as in the former place; ſo in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond place we muſt make and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temper in our meditations the thoughts of mercy with the thoughts of juſtice. Thirdly, though the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:150077:72"/>of ſin may be ſhort, yet the paſſion will be long. A ſin may be ſoon committed, but the pardon of ſin is not ſo ſoon had.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That before we can ſenſibly or ſafely Preach the mercies of God in the forgiveneſſe of ſins unto you, we muſt acquaint you with the juſtice of God, as in the verſe before my Text. <hi>If thou entreſt into Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who ſhall ſtand? But there is mercy with thee,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that thou maiſt be feared.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was the method that was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes uſed in the Old and New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament. Our firſt parents hiding themſelves through terrour of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit among the buſhes, when God would Preach the Goſpel unto them, he firſt arraigns them, and then paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes a promiſe of mercy, <hi>That the ſeed of the woman ſhould break the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents head.</hi> Thus it was in the Law, before a man could know God, he muſt come to Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> and the
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:150077:72"/>Law is a Schoolmaſter to lead us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt. Thus it was at the giving of the holy Ghoſt, <hi>there was a ruſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a mighty wind,</hi> and then the holy Ghoſt came into their mindes and hearts. This was the method of that Preacher; then in the New Teſtament, firſt, men muſt be weary and heavy laden, and then Chriſt comes to eaſe, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.8. <hi>I came not to call the righteous</hi> (thoſe that imagine themſelves ſo) <hi>but ſinners to repentance,</hi> thoſe that are ſo wiſe to ſee it, and ſo humble to ſay it. No expectation of healing from the bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen Serpent, but onely from thoſe that were hurt and look up. Firſt, ſee your ſelves led into captivity by the Devil, and then you are fit to receive infranchiſement and delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from God; and this that good Father applyed unto our ſelves. Firſt, let it be an Inſtruction for us to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, though Hell fire be flaſht in our faces, God doth it but as pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:150077:73"/>to their children, they hold them over the fire to make them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of falling into the fire. The Law is a Schoolmaſter to Chriſt. Firſt, Law and then Goſpel. Firſt, plow up the Fallow-ground of our hearts, and then ſowe the word, <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.4. according to the method of Gods appearing to <hi>Elijah;</hi> Firſt, a bluſtering wind, then an Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake, after that Fire, and laſt comes God in a ſtill voice: Firſt, look for Earthquakes, Winds, and Fires in the ſoul, and after all for comfort. Thus it is Gods moſt uſual way. And then ſecondly, what ſhall we ſay to thoſe carnal Goſpellers that are all for the calm doctrines of the times? thoſe that complain they cannot ſit quiet in their ſeats for the threatnings of ſome Miniſters, they would have a Goſpel of Gold, and Salvation of Silver, and Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of precious ſtones, and go to Heaven upon featherbeds. But
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:150077:73"/>beloved, I had rather ſpeak a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand words to comfort then one to diſcomfort, but it is for the good of your ſouls, and for the glory of our Saviour; we cannot, dare not, muſt not do otherwiſe; we muſt come home to your conſciences, come home to them; ſo the Prophets, ſo the Apoſtles have done in all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, they have denounced the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God againſt all their Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors; and did you but hear thoſe yells that are now in Hell, thoſe that cry out, I may thank that flattering Preacher for theſe pains, if he had told me of this I had not come hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Think of it now, that you feel it not hereafter. In the next place, it is good for us to temper the thoughts of mercy and juſtice toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; not to talk of juſtice onely, but alſo of mercy. <hi>My Song ſhall be of Mercy and Judgment,</hi> ſaith <hi>David, Pſalm</hi> 101.1. and <hi>Deut.</hi> 28. Half the Chapter ſpeaks of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:150077:74"/>and half of mercy, <hi>Deut.</hi> 11. <hi>Bleſsings on one Mountain, and Curſings upon another. Bleſsings upon Mount Gerizim, and curſings upon Mount E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal:</hi> And indeed there are two main rocks between which moſt men fall, Preſumption and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair; we are between them like <hi>Suſanna</hi> between the Judges; we are between them as between <hi>Sylla</hi> and <hi>Charybdis.</hi> We may ſay of Deſperation as of <hi>Saul, it hath ſlain his thouſands,</hi> but of Preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as of <hi>David, it hath ſlain his ten thouſands;</hi> and therefore though we diet our ſelves with the mercies of God, we muſt not glut with them; and this was applied by him unto the ſouls of Preacher and people: Firſt, to Preachers, we ſhould take a leſſon from hence, that when we finde that there is <hi>mors in olla,</hi> death in the pot, diſcomfort in the heart, then we muſt take the herb of comfort and put it in. That hand is hewn
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:150077:74"/>out of the hardeſt rock that will not adminiſter comfort to the ſoul that needs it. We muſt, like the good Samaritan, pour oil and wine into your ſores; wine to open them, and oil to ſupple them; ſpeak not of judgment alone; God did ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver intend this unto you, and do not deal all of mercy, but think of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment alſo; for if God had never ſo much mercy in ſtore, there is none for you preſumptuous ſinners. That was the ſecond conſideration. The third conſideration was, That though the action of ſin be ſhort, yet the paſſion is long; though a great ſin be ſoon committed, yet a ſmall ſin is not ſo ſoon remitted. Look upon <hi>David,</hi> he committed two great ſins, adultery and murder, the adultery he committed with the look of an eye, the murder with the turn of an hand, it was but writing a Letter to <hi>Joab;</hi> but though the ſtory be never ſo ſhort in <hi>Samuel,</hi> yet the repentance
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:150077:75"/>is long in the 51. <hi>Pſalm;</hi> there<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> much ado: <hi>Cauſe the bones that thou haſt broken to rejoice; Waſh me, purge me, cleanſe me, purifie me with hyſſop;</hi> the ſin of one night did cauſe the tears of many nights. Behold <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſeh,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 33.12, 13. he did pray and pray, and put up prayer upon prayer, and did humble himſelf greatly, he prayed and he prayed; this was no vain repetition, but pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er upon prayer, ſuit upon ſuit, and all little enough to obtain mercy from God; God is quickly offended, but not ſo ſoon pleaſed; the wound is ſoon taken, but not ſo ſoon cured; our ſins are compared to debts in the Lords Prayer, a man may run more into debt one day, then he can get out of many dayes; God would have it ſo that his mercy might come ſweeter unto us. See it in <hi>Joab</hi> and <hi>David, Joab</hi> intreated of <hi>David</hi> that <hi>Abſalom</hi> might come and ſee him, <hi>David</hi> was content he ſhould go to
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:150077:75"/>his houſe, but he muſt not ſee his face. Thou that ſinneſt, God may ſuffer thee to come into thy houſe, nay, into the Congregation, for the preſent, but there may be a Veil up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his face, he may not ſuffer us to ſee his face for anger. Oh then woe be to thoſe that preſume as though they had their pardon ſealed. As one relates of an uproar among the members, and the will would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the eye and the hand, you ſhall do this and that; the old Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam the fleſh wondring to hear ſuch an uproar, ſtarts up and asks the reaſon of it, ſaying, I have been quiet ſo long, and ſo I will be ſtill; you give way to ſin, but you know not which way to get out of it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, that's the main thing; the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digal ſon after his going from his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, do you think he could think of coming in a day, that was going but half a day? Is it poſſible we ſhould continue in ſin forty, fifty, ſixty years
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:150077:76"/>and then turn to God preſently? no beloved, there's more time goes to this, and therefore be not preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, take heed of truſting too much upon the mercy of God, not having an eye upon the juſtice of God, and take heed of committing ſin upon preſumption of an eaſie cure; we muſt not think to come to Heaven eaſier then <hi>David</hi> did, he cryes and he calls, he weeps and mourns like a Dove. <hi>Joſeph</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> loſt their ſon but a dayes jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, they were finding him two or three days: And thus much for the conſideration of the Text, in regard of the context, as it reflects upon the words before. Now of the Text; <hi>There is mercy with thee that thou maiſt be feared;</hi> mercy, mercy with thee: There are ſeveral kinds of mercy, the word is very large, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of prevention, and mercies of aſſiſtance, mercies of ſubvention, and mercies of ſupport; but certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:150077:76"/>the mercy of God is eſpecially in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended here, and therefore ſome Tranſlations read it, <hi>There is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs with thee that thou maiſt be feared;</hi> it is with thee, it is alwayes at home, God hath it in his hand about him, cloſe unto him, <hi>There is mercy with thee that thou maiſt be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red;</hi> and what kind of mercy? not meerly pardon of ſin, as I pardon a debt or injury, and there's an end, but the propitiation for ſins. It is in ſome Tranſlations, <hi>There is propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation with thee, &amp;c.</hi> Thus <hi>there is mercy with thee:</hi> whence ariſeth this Inſtruction, That God is prompt and ready to have mercy upon and forgive a penitent ſinner, when he ſeeks to him. I ſay; God is prompt, &amp;c. Though God be a juſt God, yet there is mercy with him. Now this mercy of God it is to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered three wayes that are very ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable: Firſt, conſider the mercy of God comparatively. Secondly,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:150077:77"/>conſider it abſolutely. Thirdly, in the circumſtances of it. Firſt, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the mercy of God compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, in reſpect of his juſtice. I know if you ſpeak of the Attributes of God, they are all Eſſential alike, but if you ſpeak of the expreſſion of them towards us, God may be ſaid to be more merciful then juſt. You ſee that God when he came to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> he came to judge him in the cool of the evening, he ſtaid long; but he ſent labourers into his Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt betimes. We find that <hi>Ninev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> had forty dayes given it before it ſhould be deſtroyed; but God made haſte, he did run to meet the prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal child, he made haſte. It is eaſie to pul down, but it is hard to build up, &amp; God takes more delight in building, then in pulling down: you ſee the mercy of God expreſſed unto <hi>Adam,</hi> unto <hi>Sodom,</hi> unto the Prodigal; and we may make compariſon of it unto the Firmament, God made it in
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:150077:77"/>one day; but God would not deſtroy the City of <hi>Nineveh</hi> under forty dayes, and many hundred years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he will deſtroy the world. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, the world was made in ſix days, but you ſee it is ſix thouſand years before he will deſtroy it; he is more prone unto mercy then unto juſtice; nay, take it in the executing of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, he ſhewed juſtice in deſtroying <hi>Sodom,</hi> but mercy in ſparing <hi>Lot,</hi> he ſhewed juſtice upon the old world, but mercy in preſerving <hi>Noah;</hi> God ſhewed his juſtice on the Jews in caſting of them off, but mercy to the Gentiles in calling of them. There was his juſtice fell upon our Saviour, but by it his mercy upon us, that from his Croſs there ſhould come cure to us. There was juſtice in ſending an Angel to deſtroy Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, but mercy in ſending another Angel to mark thoſe that mourned in Jeruſalem. Thus you ſee how God doth mingle his juſtice and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:150077:78"/>together. So <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.4, 5, 6, 7. <hi>The Lord, the Lord, merciful and gracious, abundant in, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Every word hath its weight. <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah,</hi> thou haſt broke thy promiſe with him, but he is <hi>Jehovah,</hi> and will not erre, the Lord, mighty and powerful God; it is a work of power to forgive many ſins, but he is the Lord mighty to ſave and to forgive; thou art ſinful, but God is merciful; thou art graceleſſe, but God is gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious; thou haſt broken thy vowes made unto him, but he is true of promiſe unto thee. And though thy ſins be great for quantity, and hainous for quality, he forgives ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, tranſgreſſions and ſins of all ſorts. And therefore 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. God is called <hi>the Father of mercy.</hi> The natural Bee may make honey natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, but it doth not ſting naturally, that is, not without provocation. See it alſo of God in his juſtice upon <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom;</hi> when <hi>Abraham</hi> did put up a
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:150077:78"/>ſuit for <hi>Sodom,</hi> that if there were but fifty perſons found there, he would not deſtroy it, and came down by degrees from fifty to forty, from forty to thirty, from thirty to twenty, from twenty to ten; and it is obſerved that God did never leave granting till <hi>Abraham</hi> did leave ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. It may be if he had come to leſſe, God would have ſpared them; he did ſo in another place; <hi>If there be but one to ſtand in the gap I will ſpare them.</hi> Look upon <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> a moſt abominable Idolater, who cut <hi>Eſau</hi> in pieces with an iron ſawe, and made the ſtreets of Jeruſalem to run with bloud, yet when he prayed unto God, God did forgive him. <hi>Mary Magdalene</hi> that had ſeven Devils, ſhe waſhed our Saviours feet with the hairs of her head, that had been nets to catch fools; beſtowed that coſtly ointment which ſhe had uſed upon her ſelf, upon Chriſt. Chriſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of it, he applauds it, he rewards
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:150077:79"/>it; he is prone unto mercy, and more prone unto mercy then unto judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The Prodigal ſon when he returns home to his Father, his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther runs and meets him when he was afar off, and he doth not ſtrike him or chide him, but he falls upon his neck, puts his ring upon his finger. The Shepherd when he findes his ſheep that was loſt, he doth not beat it, but he laies it upon his neck. Thirdly, conſider the circumſtances of this mercy. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider firſt, who it is that doth forgive. Who? why the God of Heaven and Earth, he that hath Vials of wrath in his hand, and could pour them upon us, we that are his inferiours and his enemies: we though we do bear with our ſuperiours, we will trample upon our inferiours; but God doth not ſo.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Conſider what God in mercy doth forgive us, and that is ſin. <hi>Bleſſed are they whoſe iniquities
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:150077:79"/>are forgiven, and whoſe ſin is pardoned. David</hi> doth not place his bleſſings in his Beauty, <hi>he was ruddy of complex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion;</hi> nor in his government, though he was a great King; nor in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, he was taken from the ſheep to be head over Iſrael: But here is his happineſſe, <hi>Bleſſed is he whoſe iniquities are forgiven, and whoſe ſin is pardoned.</hi> Nay, how often doth God do this? ſeven times? no, but as often as Chriſt commands us to forgive our brethren, ſeventy ſeven times, as often as we forgive our brethren, ſo we offend not out of malice, but return and repent, God will have mercy on us. There went but one word to the making of the world, but there go many to the ſaving of a ſoul, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8. And now judge and examine if you can ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine what a depth and height there is in this mercy of God. I come to the Application in brief, and ſo to put an end to this Sermon. This
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:150077:80"/>may be an Antidote, a Preſervative againſt deſperation unto poor deject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſouls and diſconſolate ſinners, that God is as merciful as juſt, and delights more in mercy then in ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice. What a precious balſome is this for a wounded ſinner? And conſider firſt, that deſperation it is moſt injurious unto our ſelves, a wound that cannot poſſibly be healed by us. If a Chirurgeon laies on a plaiſter, and we caſt it away, what hope is there of cure for us? And if God ſends us the comforts of the Goſpel, and if we ſit down ſullen and caſt them away, what comfort can we have? Deſperation is compared to a beaſt with horns, it puſhes againſt mercy. What for a man to deſpair of mercy, is it but to ſpill his bloud upon the ground, or to throw it in the air, with <hi>Julian,</hi> or to hang it on a Tree, with <hi>Judas?</hi> that God ſhould drink to us in a cup of ſalvation, and we to pledge him
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:150077:80"/>in a cup of damnation, that is dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory from God: The Devil comes to us, and ſayes, Thy ſins are too great, the mercies of God are too precious for thee; ſhall we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that lyar, rather then he that ſayes, <hi>I have been wounded for you, I will take your ſins upon me, and heal you?</hi> Will you make God a lyar, and the Devil true?</p>
            <p>Secondly, look upon the ſteps of deſperation, the ſeveral ſteps of it, he did name divers
<note n="*" place="margin">Ingratitude Infidelity.</note> ſteps, but inſiſted only upon this, to wit, Preſumption. The wicked man begins in preſumption, but ends in deſpair. When their flatteries have touled them a long time on, and perſwaded them that their caſe is good, at laſt their ſouls are ſtifled with the conſideration of their ſins by preſumption: what more contrary? and yet preſumption it is the very rode way to deſperation. If I am abroad long, either in the
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:150077:81"/>Sun, or in the Snow, my eyes will be ſo dazeled I ſhall hardly ſee. When I have been in the glorious Sun-ſhine of the mercy of God, in the Halcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on dayes of proſperity, I cannot taſte any thing but of a Saviour. A preſumptuous man is like unto one that is aſleep upon a rock, and dreaming of a rock of Pearl ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtarts up and falls into the Sea. Take heed the Devil do not finde you upon this pinacle, upon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, and ſo caſt you down to eternal deſtruction. Shall I be bold and preſumptuous, becauſe God is merciful? Shall I cut and gaſh my ſelf, becauſe a good Chirurgeon lives where I live? Shall I uſe ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacles to go over a Bridge to make the Bridge ſeem better, and ſo periſh? Look not upon the mercy as if it were greater then it is; no, as God is merciful to penitent, ſo he is juſt to impenitent ſinners.</p>
            <pb n="145" facs="tcp:150077:81"/>
            <p>And ſo this reverend Father of our Church who was in Heaven while he was on Earth, preached againſt thoſe two main enemies of our ſalvation, Deſperation and Preſumption; His words were all excellent, of the juſtice and mercy of God, and the merits of our Saviour. But what will become of all this? what comfort ſprings from the mercy of God, from the forgiveneſſe of ſins unto us, if our hearts, our thoughts creep ſtill on the ground, if we be taken up with Earthly things, and prefer ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and honour before God? and therefore came to the chance of our fourth and laſt Divine, to draw up our hearts, <hi>(ſurſum corda)</hi> unto Heaven. If you look for mercy lift up your hearts where it is to be had; wherefore ſhould we look down, or kill flies any longer? our converſations muſt be in Heaven, if
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:150077:82"/>our hearts be in Heaven. This was the bag out of which he did fetch treaſure new and old, precious treaſure.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="sermon">
            <pb n="147" facs="tcp:150077:82"/>
            <head>A Sermon Preached by Doctor <hi>Weſphale,</hi> at the <hi>Spittle</hi> on Wedneſday in <hi>Eaſter</hi> week.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PHILIPPIANS 3.20, 21.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>But our Converſation is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, from whence we look for our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, who ſhall change our viſe bodies that they may be like unto his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious body, according to that mighty word whereby he is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſubdue all things.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE words may be read two wayes, either <hi>For our converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:150077:83"/>is in Heaven:</hi> or, <hi>But our conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation is in Heaven:</hi> If <hi>For our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation is in Heaven,</hi> it is an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to inforce a duty ſet down in the ſeventeenth verſe, That we ſhould not minde the things here below, for Saint <hi>Paul</hi> and the reſt of the Saints have their converſation in Heaven. If you will read it <hi>(but)</hi> then there's another reference in the eighteenth and nineteenth verſes. There were many falſe Apoſtles whoſe glory was their ſhame, and minded earthly things; but there was a diſtinction between true and falſe Apoſtles: <hi>But our converſation is in Heaven,</hi> whereever the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation of falſe Apoſtles is.</p>
            <p>Take it which way you will, by way of a motive, or a diſtinction; it is not ſo much for us to know what Saint <hi>Paul</hi> did, but what we ought to do, what we ſhould do. There are four things conſiderable in the Text: Firſt, that the Chriſtians
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:150077:83"/>converſation it is in Heaven. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, his expectation, he looks for our Lord and Saviour there. Thirdly, his happineſſe, <hi>who ſhall change our vile bodies, and make them like unto his glorious body.</hi> Fourthly, the ground of this hope and confidence, <hi>according to that mighty power where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he is able to ſubdue all things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having taken his riſe from the firſt of theſe, the Chriſtians conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, <hi>But our converſation is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi> The word <hi>Converſation</hi> is in the Old Teſtament every where up and down. For <hi>Converſation</hi> the word here uſed is <hi>Politeuma,</hi> and it is a word that concerns thoſe that live in Cities. So <hi>Greg. Nazianzen, Beza</hi> and <hi>Tertullian,</hi> do interpret it. <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith, <hi>But our Burgeſsſhip is in Heaven;</hi> and ſo <hi>Beza, We are Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes or freemen of Heaven.</hi> But <hi>Beza</hi> and the reſt they have faln ſhort of this <hi>Politeuma:</hi> It ſignifies more then a Burgeſsſhip or freedome, but
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:150077:84"/>they are Citizens; you make many free that are far from you; you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count them onely Citizens that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habit among you. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> himſelf from rods, by ſaying he was a Roman, but yet he was born at <hi>Tarſus;</hi> he was free there, but yet he was not a true Citizen there: So there is a <hi>medium</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween theſe two. So <hi>Anaxagoras</hi> when it was laid to his charge, that he followed his ſtudy ſo much that he did not care for his Countrey, no, ſaith he, but I do, and pointing up his finger, ſaid, that Heaven was his Countrey, I care for that. So ſaith <hi>David, I am a ſtranger;</hi> he was not onely a ſtranger when he was in <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtia,</hi> with the King of <hi>Gath,</hi> but in this earth, as <hi>all my fathers were.</hi> When I am at home, I am not at home; though I am in my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, yet I am not in my own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey: <hi>For our converſation is in Heaven.</hi> Heaven it is the Haven of
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:150077:84"/>the Saints, God hath prepared Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for them, and them for Heaven. There are two Cities whereof Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, the one he calls Heaven, the other Earth, the one <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the other. <hi>Babylon;</hi> Let every man conſider to which City he belongs, for all of us belong either to <hi>Babylon</hi> or <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> either above or below. <hi>Monicha</hi> the mother of Saint <hi>Auſtin,</hi> when ſhe ſaw her ſon converted, cryes out, <hi>Neſcio quid faciam,</hi> &amp;c. 'Tis true the time was that I deſired ſome length of time to ſee thee become a good Chriſtian, but now I ſee that performed, what if I dye, if I dye, now I ſee my ſon a true Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Chriſtian, and a right honeſt man? ſhe cared for no more. But if you will ask the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> eſpecially the more Ancient, or ſome others before the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> came into the world, they will ſay an Hermites life is that which is the moſt Heavenly. As <hi>Paul</hi> the Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:150077:85"/>prefers a Monaſtical life, as if Saint <hi>Paul</hi> had ſaid, <hi>In Cellis,</hi> and not <hi>In Celſis, in Caves,</hi> and not <hi>in Heaven:</hi> But that life though it keeps them from a great deal of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, ſo it hinders them from doing a great deal of good: a contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive life it may be a blear-eyed life; A contemplative life were good, if God had no other buſineſſe for us in this world but to leave our parents and friends, our profeſſions and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and to run into Cells; this is not the right converſation. We may uſe the world, but not love it, ſaith Saint <hi>Paul;</hi> uſe the world, but not abuſe it, by riot, gluttony, ſurfets, exceſſe, which is a fighting with God with his own weapons; if you love the world, you do abuſe the world. But now let us conſider our ſelves, what we are. There are many in the world that have nothing to do in the world but to care for the world: <hi>They are of the earth, earthly,</hi>
               <pb n="153" facs="tcp:150077:85"/>as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, that think of the earth, talk of the earth, and do nothing but trade in the earth: So that ſilver and gold may flow in, they deſire no more, they ſee nothing ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient but that. To whom ſhall I liken this generation? to Bees and to Ants. The Ants they are a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a wiſe Nation, as <hi>Solomon</hi> calls them, though not a ſtrong, there is an Ariſtocracy among them. But now there are the Bees, and they have a Monarchy, and they are buſie too. So alſo men are wiſe in their generation this way, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that Summer will not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes laſt, but that Winter will come; that health will not laſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, but ſickneſſe will come: But Oh who looks for their ſouls? who provides that when Earth forſakes them, Heaven may finde them? I will give you the character of thoſe whoſe converſations are in Heaven, to characteriſe them: We uſe to
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:150077:86"/>ſay of a man that's dead, he is a man of another world; and ſo true Chriſtians they are men of another world. 'Tis true you finde them here, but they are here and not here; while they are below, they are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove. They do not ſlight the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors of God in the world, but they do not uſe them as though they loved them. They do not hate the world, nor do they fear the frown of the world. A good Chriſtian takes care to ſhift himſelf out of the world with faith and a good Conſcience, with the peace of God. 'Tis true he is imparted in worldly things, but he hath an heavenly minde. He never ventures upon any worldly buſineſſe, but his thoughts and his heart are lifted up in the midſt of his worldly buſineſſe, with many ejaculations and ſhort prayers. When things fall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ccording to his expectation, he ſings Hallelujah's and <hi>Hoſanna</hi>'s; when things fall out croſly, he looks
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:150077:86"/>for better dayes to come; he hath ſorrow here, but joyes hereafter: He will lighten himſelf in any ſtorm, by caſting his eſtate away, one thing one way, and another thing another way, ſo he may come ſafe to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. His eyes are upon that Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtial place where the Angels are, and the ſpirits of juſt men made perfect, and where the body is, to which the Eagles do reſort; and they look for our Saviour Chriſt from thence: and that leads me from the firſt part, which is the Chriſtians converſation, unto the ſecond, the Chriſtians ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation. From whence we look for our Lord, &amp;c. And herein there are three particulars conſiderable:</p>
            <p>Firſt, the perſon expected, our Lord and Saviour. Secondly, the place from whence he is expected, from Heaven: And thirdly, the act it ſelf, Expectation.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the perſon expected, our Lord and Saviour, Jeſus and Chriſt,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:150077:87"/>both anſwer one another; the two latter are but explicable to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; not to hold you long upon theſe beginnings of Divinity, although they are profitable: Firſt, he is our Jeſus, our Saviour. Our Saviour ſaith <hi>Tully,</hi> what word's that? reading it in an Inſcription over a door in <hi>Syracuſe:</hi> What mean the words? <hi>Non poſſunt exprimi,</hi> it cannot be expreſſed with one word. Will you ſay it is <hi>Serva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> or <hi>Salvator?</hi> it is a made word. <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his <hi>African</hi> Language, will call it <hi>Salutifica;</hi> but this comes from the former. Well, but ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtin,</hi> he is a Saviour which is a Saviour, and will be a Saviour. He came at the firſt to ſave our bodies from ſin, he ſhall come to ſave our ſouls, and he ſhall come from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. This is the name by which we muſt look to be ſaved, and there is no other name under Heaven. He is a Lord alſo as well as a Jeſus: Lord is a name of honour, and a name of
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:150077:87"/>power. A name of honour, and therefore given unto Kings, unto Prieſts, unto Prophets, and unto great men. Unto Kings; <hi>My Lord the King</hi> every where uſed. Unto Prieſts; ſo <hi>Hannah</hi> unto <hi>Eli.</hi> To the Prophets; ſo to <hi>Eliſha.</hi> To great men; ſo to <hi>Naaman</hi> the Syrian; <hi>My Lord, if the Prophet,</hi> &amp;c. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt being a greater King then <hi>David,</hi> a greater Prieſt then <hi>Eli,</hi> a greater Prophet then <hi>Eliſha,</hi> doth well deſerve this title of Lord. And ſecondly, in regard of power, there is in Chriſt a double power; there is <hi>poteſtas innata,</hi> and <hi>poteſtas data,</hi> a power innate, and a power given. And he is ſometimes called the Lord, with addition, the Lord of the world, the Lord of his Church; ſometimes he is called the Lord, by way of Appropriation, <hi>My Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> my God,</hi> ſaith <hi>Thomas: The Lord ſaid unto my Lord,</hi> ſaith <hi>David.</hi> Sometimes in a way of Foundation, <hi>My Lord the
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:150077:88"/>King;</hi> but what's the Lord without his honour? If Chriſt be a Lord, then in the firſt place let us honour him. <hi>If I be a Lord, where is my fear?</hi> Secondly, let us obey him: To give him the name, and to deny obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, it were to mock him. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſubmit to his Law in all things whatſoever; <hi>It is the Lord,</hi> ſaith <hi>Eli, let him do what ſeemeth good in his own eyes.</hi> Fourthly, you muſt part with any thing for this God. They let <hi>looſe the Foal and the Aſſe, becauſe the Lord hath need of them.</hi> It is the Lords, wherefore wilt thou keep it from him?</p>
            <p>Fifthly, take heed of giving thy ſelf over to any luſt to be Lord; Pride would be Lord, (as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith) Idleneſſe would be my Lord, Vain-gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> would be my Lord, but thou onely ſhalt be my Lord.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, we muſt not uſe our own means; we cannot ſay our tongues are our own, our hands are our own,
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:150077:88"/>we have a Lord over them and us. You that are Lords on earth, have a Lord in Heaven; You that are Kings on earth, have a King in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, we muſt expect this Lord, we muſt look for him. And ſo I come from the firſt particular of this general, the perſon expected, to the ſecond, the place from whence he is expected, and that's from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; <hi>But our converſation is in the Heavens.</hi> Out of which Heavens we muſt expect our Saviour; it is a diſſonant in the expreſſion, and it is but a circumſtance, but we muſt pauſe upon it. Heaven is the place from whence we expect Chriſt. When Chriſt is in Heaven, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be on earth: Chriſt is not upon the earth bodily, as the Papiſts would have him, but he is now in Heaven, and the <hi>Heavens muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain him till the time of the reſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all things.</hi> 'Tis true, Chriſt
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:150077:89"/>is here by his protecting power, by his Word and by his Love, and by his Spirit he walks amidſt the golden Candleſticks. <hi>I am he,</hi> you know the Text ſaith, but not in a bodily way, he hath not loſt the eſſential property of his Godhead, he is in all places in heavenly things, he hath called us together to ſit down with him not onely in hope; we are in Heaven even while we are on earth. <hi>Securi eſtis, &amp;c.</hi> ſaith <hi>Tertullian: Oh my fleſh and ſpirit be you ſecure, Chriſt is gone to prepare Heaven for you;</hi> he is gone, he hath left us the pledge of his Spirit that he will come to us, and he hath taken with him the pledge of our fleſh to aſſure us that we ſhall come to him. What would we have more? What better rock can we reſt upon then this, our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our is in Heaven? There's a double expectation of our Saviour Chriſt: Firſt, his firſt coming was expected; <hi>Oh that thou wouldſt rend the Heavens
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:150077:89"/>and come down!</hi> Eſa. 66. <hi>He is called the deſire of the Nations.</hi> Heb. 2. <hi>The hope of the people of God.</hi> We ſee how <hi>Hannah</hi> the Propheteſſe, and the reſt, did wait for the coming of Chriſt; and there's another expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that's of the ſecond co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt: And thus we muſt expect our Saviour, but how? after what manner? There are many conditions we muſt expect him in: We muſt firſt look for him with faith, and with aſſurance that <hi>he that ſhall come will come, and will not tarry;</hi> he will come in his own time, but we muſt wait for him. Secondly, we muſt wait for his coming with the love of his coming. There are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny accuſed as Malefactors, that look for the Judge to come to abſolve them, and to deliver them out of priſon; Others to condemn them: one looks with an hateful and an angry eye, the other with a loving, expecting, and a longing eye: So
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:150077:90"/>the Saints of Chriſt, they wait and long for his coming, they are ſick of love, and deſire to be united to him, not with remiſſe affections, but with ardent love, intenſively, and yet patiently expecting him. To him that believes, he will make haſte to come and ſup with him. <hi>Even ſo, Come Lord Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And then laſtly, we muſt look for this coming of our Saviour with care and with Conſcience; 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.11. <hi>We look for a new Heaven, and a new Earth,</hi> according to his promiſe. Conſider therefore what manner of perſons we ought to be, if we look for the Reſurrection, for Chriſts co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in all holineſſe. The word in the Original is <hi>in all holineſſes.</hi> There <hi>are many have forms of godlines, but they deny the power of it.</hi> Oh the ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the lying, the Sabbath-breaking, the murdering, the abuſe and injuring one of another! doth this fit us for the coming of Chriſt? with what
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:150077:90"/>tongues can we ſay, <hi>Come Lord Jeſus,</hi> when we live ſo baſely, and entertain ſuch horrid crimes? we muſt be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full as well as expecting Chriſtians; we muſt live in heaven, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore expect our Saviour thence, <hi>that he may change our vile bodies to be like unto his glorious body, when he ſhall come in glory.</hi> The very creatures groan for the coming of Chriſt, the very creatures deſire a diſſolution, and much more Chriſtians. It is to put forth the horn and the head as a Watch-man out of his Tower, to ſee who draws neer, or whether it be day or no: So we muſt long and look for the coming of our Saviour, and that we may enjoy happineſs of him, <hi>that he may change our vile bodies to be like unto his glorious body.</hi> And ſo I come unto the third particular, the happineſſe of the Saints.</p>
            <p>And firſt, here we may ſee what our bodies are; and ſecondly, what they ſhall be: They are for the
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:150077:91"/>preſent vanity, they ſhall be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. Firſt, what they are for the preſent, <hi>vile,</hi> vile bodies; I may ſay, bodies of vileneſs. But you will ſay, do not I derogate from my God, to call it a vile body? No, I may honour my God, and diſhonour my body. It is his glory that he hath put ſuch treaſure in earthen and vile veſſels, that he ſhould transform a vile into a glorious body. This is his honour: Let me a little ſet a gloſſe upon the body, before I call it vile. The body of man it is Gods Maſter-piece, an Artificial work. The other works of God may be called the works of his fingers, but the body of man is called the work of Gods hands. I am curiouſly wrought, I am wonderfully made: Look upon the embroidery of thy veins, upon thy ſinews, how intire, how interwoven and intertwiſted; the countenance of man looks up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, when all beaſts look down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards;
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:150077:91"/>and though there be many faces, yet all agree in one viſage, and yet they all differ in ſomething: the eye of man it is the watch-man of the ſoul, it is a moſt goodly part, &amp; a prime piece of Architecture; and the hand it is an inſtrument of inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, how eaſily and quickly we can call it from one affair unto ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther! And yet though this body be ſo glorious, you ſee what we have made it, a vile body; a vile body in three reſpects:</p>
            <p>Firſt of all, in reſpect of the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of it, and that whereof it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded. Secondly, in reſpect of the accidents unto which it is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. Thirdly, in reſpect of the cloſe and concluſion of all, of that into which it ſhall be once turned.</p>
            <p>Firſt, inſpect of the original of our bodies: What are they but earth? The name <hi>Adam</hi> will minde us of it, it ſignifies earth, earth comes of earth, nay, it comes of clay, ſaith <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liphaz</hi>
               <pb n="166" facs="tcp:150077:92"/>in <hi>Job;</hi> nay, not ſo properly, our bodies are ſo many diſordered matters, not earth but duſt; duſt, the worſt and moſt contemptible; nay, not duſt, rather out of the duſt, if there be any thing worſe then duſt in duſt, of that was man made: You ſee from whence we come, though that <hi>Abſalom</hi> and <hi>Adonijah</hi> were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo proper, and tall, and beautiful, yet for all that they come from the earth, they were but a piece of duſt and clay; though you be never ſo beautiful, or never ſo artificially a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorn your ſelves, though you do frizzle and circumciſe your ſelves, you do but adorn a piece of clay, a piece of earth: Suppoſe you do wear gold, and jewels, and precious ſtones, yet you cannot make it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then a vile body, a vile piece of earth. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> gives it the right name, <hi>a piece of earth, a vile body.</hi> Again, ſuppoſe the body were never ſo ſeemingly beautiful,
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:150077:92"/>or better inveſted or clothed then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, yet all is earth; the Debtor and the Creditor, the King and the ſubject, the Noble and the Peaſant, all vile, all earth. We have our fair <hi>China</hi>-diſhes, yet we account them but earth, all earth as well as other veſſels. Put ſilver into an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then veſſel, it is ſtill earthen: and this is the nature of our bodies in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of their original.</p>
            <p>Again, in the ſecond place, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the ſeveral caſualties to which our bodies are obnoxious; you ſee how we are ſubject to hunger, and thirſt, and cold, theſe are natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, the body is inveſted and ſhrowded with theſe. But for caſualties; our bodies are ſubject to be burned, hanged, drowned: by which we may ſee that man is but meer vanity; and though all things come by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God, yet we may call them caſualties. We are ſubject to many infirmities: How many diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:150077:93"/>are there in this body? <hi>Pliny</hi> faith in his time there were three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred diſeaſes; and how many diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes are there in this old and decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit age? an hundred and twelve diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes of the eyes, in the breaſt, in the head, in the heart. I cannot ſtand to inſtance in all: you ſee how we are infeſted and troubled with all theſe, and for our cures of them trees and berries, herbs, and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and parts of beaſts, and all lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle enough; beholden to all things for every thing; to the Hart for the horn, to the Oxe for the gall; nay, that which we ſcorn to touch in our health, we are beholding to in our ſickneſs, as Doves dung, poiſon, and the like. Will you conclude now that theſe bodies are vile? May I not ſay with Saint <hi>Bernard,</hi> that the body it is a Magazine of miſery, a ſink and puddle of corruption?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it is vile alſo in reſpect of the concluſion, the end and cloſe
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:150077:93"/>of it, <hi>We are duſt, and unto duſt we muſt return, Eccleſ.</hi> 12.7. <hi>Sarah</hi> though ſhe were never ſo beautiful in the eyes of <hi>Abraham,</hi> yet he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires a piece of ground of the <hi>Ekro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites</hi> to bury his dead out of his ſight, he could not endure her in his ſight. Many times our bodies are buried in the bellies of beaſts, as it was with <hi>Jezebel,</hi> (as your Preacher told you) in the bellies of Fiſhes, as <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and many in the mawes of birds, as many ſlain in battel. When we come to the moſt honourable bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial, the beſt is to go to the Earth, and what becomes of us then? why then we are food for the worms; ſometimes they lay hold upon us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we come to the grave, ſo on <hi>Herod, Theocrates,</hi> and <hi>Sylla</hi> the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctator, and <hi>Maximinus,</hi> all eaten of worms. Take heed, there are worms creep out of a man before he dies; There was an Heathen that had this diſeaſe, and deſired that the
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:150077:94"/>Chriſtians might not hear of it. And a King within our memory, in theſe Weſtern parts, did call his ſon upon his death-bed, and ſhewed him theſe beaſts upon his breaſt, which ſtruck him to the heart that he died. <hi>Job</hi> was troubled with the worms too, <hi>Job</hi> 7. <hi>full of worms;</hi> and God threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens to <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> Eſa. 14. <hi>That there ſhould be worms beneath him, and worms above him, worms ſhould be his covering.</hi> Conſider this, you that do pamper your ſelves, as if you ſhould never die, this is all you can do, you do but make the more meat for worms, and the more fleſh you have, the more meat you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for worms. Conſider this, you that tumble over in your wardrobes, you do but clothe and adorn that which is worms meat in time. You that boaſt ſo of your pedegree and deſcent, and you will not take it as you have done, go to <hi>Job</hi> and <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> they will tell you what your
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:150077:94"/>kindred is; <hi>I have ſaid unto a worm, thou art my father, and unto rottenneſs, thou art my mother.</hi> Thus you ſee what we are, food for worms; but let us take heed we meet not with another worm, and that's the worm of Conſcience, it is no matter though other worms eat us. <hi>Though I be meat for worms,</hi> ſaith <hi>Job, yet I know that my Redeemer lives, and that I ſhall ſee him with theſe eyes, &amp;c. But the worm of Conſcience ſhall never die, the fire of Hell ſhall never go out.</hi> And if your bodies be vile of themſelves, make them not viler. The Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard he makes himſelf a ſwine, and the Glutton he makes it an hoggeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, the adulterer makes his body the member of an harlot; yet with a good Conſcience, though this be our miſery, that they are vile bodies, yet this ſhall be our happineſs, that <hi>they ſhall be made like unto his glorious body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And there are four ſpecial in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:150077:95"/>or privileges of a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious body, Impaſſibility, Activity, Spirituality and Clarity: Firſt Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſibility; we ſhall be paſt ſuffering at the laſt day; <hi>ſentire eſt pati,</hi> even to feel is to ſuffer now, and in every action there is a paſſion; but it ſhall not be ſo hereafter, when our bodies ſhall be changed, then there ſhall be no ſorrow, no fainting, no crying: Farewel Gout, and Stone, and Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gury, and all; if I ſhall be brought to happineſs, I ſhall be brought to ſafety.</p>
            <p>Secondly, there is Activity; here our bodies are dull and ſlow, theſe Aſſes of ours muſt be beaten, and ſpurr'd, and whipt to do any good; our ſpirit may be willing, when our fleſh is weak. It ſhall not be ſo here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, we ſhall be vigorous, and active, and lively, and theſe our bodies which are now ſo dull, ſhall be then lively, and go on with cheerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <pb n="173" facs="tcp:150077:95"/>
            <p>And thirdly, it is a ſpiritual body; <hi>corpus ſpirituale,</hi> a ſpiritual body, but not a ſpirit; it ſhall be ſpiritual, but not a ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, it ſhall be a clear body, a clarified body, that's the fourth prerogative of a glorified body, <hi>Daniel</hi> 12.1. <hi>The righteous ſhall ſhine like the ſtars in the Firmament, and thoſe that convert many to righteouſneſs, like the Sun for ever and ever;</hi> nay, more then this, our Saviour goes farther, <hi>they ſhall ſhine,</hi> ſicut Sol in poteſtate, <hi>like the Sun in its ſtrength;</hi> yet farther here in the Text, <hi>our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies ſhall be like unto his glorious body.</hi> What ſayeſt thou, <hi>Paul,</hi> faith Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> to Saint <hi>Paul</hi> here, Doſt thou know what thou ſayeſt? What like unto Chriſts glorious body? That body that ſits at Gods right hand? that body that is worſhipped by Angels? Yes, like unto his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious body. Let me then look for the ſaving of my ſoul: Let the
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:150077:96"/>world weep for what they pleaſe, I will weep more for the loſſe of my body and ſoul. I wonder, ſaith Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> That men ſhould give away their ſouls, throw them away upon trifles, to diſrobe themſelves of this tranſcendent glory, to loſe ſuch a glory as this is, to be made like unto the glorious body of our Saviour. Wilt thou caſt away this ſoul? what a madneſſe is it of thee? Many men do compare the pain of loſſe with the pain of ſence which the damned have in Hell, and do think the pain of loſſe to be worſe then the pain of ſence. To loſe the ſight of my Saviour, to loſe this glory that I ſhould have arrived at, this ſticks more at me then all the pains of Hell could do, ſo I may enjoy my God. O Lord, whatever thou takeſt from me, take not from me this glory, this eternal glory: Lord, here cut me, and ſlay me, do what thou wilt with me, onely ſave
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:150077:96"/>my ſoul. There are many loſſes in this world, of husbands, of children, of goods by unfaithful ſervants, by fire, by irreligious and prodigal chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; but theſe are not to be named when we ſpeak of the loſſe of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. And therefore to conclude this point, I loſe my father, my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, my husband, my wiſe, my chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; but from this, this loſſe, this eternal loſſe of the ſoul, good Lord deliver us.</p>
            <p>And thus much the fourth Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher. He was alſo even in Heaven while he was on earth, as his Text ſpeaks, <hi>Our converſation is in Heaven;</hi> and if ever there were a lively Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary upon the Text, his Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was the Commentary it ſelf, he was an example next to the example of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> while he preached he ſpake as if he had been in Heaven.</p>
            <pb n="176" facs="tcp:150077:97"/>
            <p>And thus have I run this race, done this task laid upon me, with my ſmall abilities: I hope you will not lay unto my charge the ſlips, the infirmities which have paſſed from me.</p>
            <p>The three laſt, they were old Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples of Chriſt, they made among them two hundred and thirty or two hundred and forty years; Chriſt doth love old Diſciples, and he loves young ones; he loves old Diſciples, becauſe they hold out ſo long, and he loves young Diſciples, becauſe they begin ſo ſoon. <hi>Juniores Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulos Chriſtus diligit,</hi> &amp;c. Chriſt lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved his young Diſciples beſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they began early; he loves his old Diſciples, becauſe they cleave cloſely unto him. But the Tyrant time requires another diſcourſe of me; but I muſt tell you before hand that it will be but as a dinner of
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:150077:97"/>herbs after a Feaſt of fat things: Take it as it is.</p>
            <p>You have heard of the death of our Saviour, in the firſt; of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of our Saviour, and of his manner of riſing, in the ſecond; you have heard of the mercy of God in the forgiveneſſe of ſin, propounded to all that ſerve him in an heavenly converſation, in the third; and of our body by an heavenly converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion transformed to be like unto his glorious body, in the fourth. Theſe are rare myſteries, and when we have ſaid all we can, we muſt break off with ſilence, with amazement and ſtupefaction. Theſe are deep myſteries, we are not able to ſound them with our corrupt judgement; <hi>Great is the myſtery of Godlineſs, God manifeſt in the fleſh, ſeen of Angels, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are not able to conceive of
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:150077:98"/>him, we cannot expreſſe him; and therefore I think it will cohere with the matter in hand to diſplay before your eyes the profoundneſſe of theſe myſteries; which we may ſee in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.9.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="sermon">
            <pb n="179" facs="tcp:150077:98"/>
            <head>A Sermon Preached by Maſter <hi>Price</hi> at S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church, on <hi>Low-Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, May</hi> 2. 1641.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 CORINTHIANS 13.9.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>For we know but in part, and we prophecie but in part.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>AS the eleventh Chapter of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> may be called the Triumph of Faith, ſo this Chapter may be well ſtiled the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph of Love. Which triumphant grace, beſides that it is inveſted with admirable qualities, and ſeconded by glorious effects; and beſides that it
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:150077:99"/>bears away the bell from the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the brain, from the prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of the tongue, the eloquence of that little member, the munificence of the hand, and the Martyrdome of the whole body. All which we find ſpoken of in this Chapter. Without love, what is faith but fancie? what is prophecie but a dark myſtery? what is eloquence but untunable muſick? what is munificence but prodigality? what is martyrdome but a raſh and unadviſed ſlaying a mans ſelf? Without love they may all hang down in their own weakneſſe and infirmity; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Saint <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, <hi>We know but in part,</hi> and therefore <hi>prophecie but in part; We know but in part,</hi> that's the firſt, and I fear the time will ſuffer me to go no farther. <hi>We know but in part.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Take knowledge to be what you will, take it at the largeſt extent, the wiſeſt men on earth, thoſe that
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:150077:99"/>have been in the uppermoſt cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Divinity, and ſounded the depths of all Learning, yea, that have gone round all humane Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they know but in part. Some things there are that we know not, and there are ſome things we know but in part; and what we know ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectively, it may be full, but ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively, it is weak.</p>
            <p>Firſt, ſome things we know not, as the Eſſence of God, inſtant in things paſt and to come, we cannot know it, it is not fit for our under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. Who knows what God did before the world? Who knows when the Angels were crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? who knows? we may collect and conjecture, but who can poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively affirm it? who can tell whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Sun before the Stars were created, did riſe and ſet, or no? thoſe are beyond our knowledge. We know not the end of the world, when all things ſhall be out of date,
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:150077:100"/>when the tongue ſhall be tied up from prophecying in this world, when faith ſhall be turned into fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe, and hope into quaking; and that when hope ſhall quake, love ſhall ſtand ſtill when the reſt faint and vaniſh. This is confirmed in the words neer the Text, and in the words of my Text. The Argument ſtands thus; That which is but in part cannot laſt; But knowledg is but in part, and faith is but in part; <hi>For we know but in part, and we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie but in part:</hi> And beloved, if ſo be theſe Preachers you have heard have faln ſhort in any particular in the proſecution of their Text; and if I, (as I know I muſt) being weary of proceeding, and I undervalue my own thoughts, neither will I be ſo in love with the brood of my own brain, as to trouble you and my ſelf long with it, but onely in behalf of all the Miniſters that have preached, and of my ſelf, that <hi>we know but in
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:150077:100"/>part, and prophecie but in part.</hi> The head and tongue divide the Text; the head is like unto Heaven, that doth diſperſe abroad its light and influence by the tongue; and the tongue it is a many-ſtringed inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whereby we do praiſe God. Here's the knowledge of the head, the tongue, but that this tongue may be tied up from ſelf-commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, therefore we come to the ignorant terms of antipathy; as, Why doth the Load-ſtone draw Iron to it? what anſwer can we give, but that it is the quality? as much as to ſay, I do not know: And ſo for the times to come, it is not for us to know the times of God. Prophecies are beſt underſtood in the fulfilling of them; there are many things God hath left to his own Cabinet-Councel, and we muſt not intrude into them; <hi>Secret things belong to God, but revealed things to as and to our children.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="184" facs="tcp:150077:101"/>
            <p>And ſecondly, our knowledge is but imperfect, in reſpect of the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, <hi>We ſee but through a glaſs darkly and imperfectly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, what can we ſay or know of God? <hi>Damaſin</hi> ſaith, he is not an eſſence or ſubſtance, he is ſomewhat above; we do not know what to call him; bring in a contribution of all kind of language, there's too much inability to expreſſe the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Almighty God; our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God riſes not by adding to it, but as a ſtatue riſes, by cutting ſomewhat from it, and we know him by an imperfect knowledge. We ſee the Sun in a dim kind of way; we ſee but the back-parts of God, as we ſee a man that is paſt, we have but a glimpſe of it. And ſo for the Trinity, the Father, Son, and holy Ghoſt, three Perſons, and one God; it is a myſtery, that made <hi>Hillary</hi> cry out, and fall back, and go again, and ſay, there's a ſtupidity in my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding,
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:150077:101"/>I know not what to ſay: and therefore the <hi>Nicene</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers would not have the words of Eſſence uſed, they thought there was more in God. And ſo for the Decree of God, how far is it beyond our knowledge? <hi>How unſearchable are his Judgments? they are paſt find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out.</hi> And if you cannot finde out the reaſon of Gods decrees, ſee the reaſon of it, it is well for you to be of his Court, though not of his Councel. His decrees may amaze a man to conſider them; read but Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> diſcourſe, how ſhall we puzzle and gravel? what ſhall we ſay more then this I will not ſay: Do thou reaſon the caſe how thou wilt, <hi>Ego credam,</hi> I will believe.</p>
            <p>And then fourthly, for the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the world; what a vaſt diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is there between nothing and ſomething? We may believe there is a Creation, but we cannot graſp it in our underſtanding.</p>
            <pb n="186" facs="tcp:150077:102"/>
            <p>And then in the fifth place, the prophanation of ſin, That God ſhould create us ſo holy that the body ſhould have no ſin in it, and yet there ſhould now be ſin in both body &amp; ſoul; we know it. But how do we know it? Come to the Perſon and Offices of Chriſt, that he that was the Ancient of dayes ſhould dye; that he that was the mouth of his Father, and the Word, ſhould not ſpeak, this is a myſtery, and great is the myſtery. And then again, the myſtery or our bodies, that our bodies ſhould be deſtroyed, that they ſhould be turned to aſhes, or cut in pieces, and one piece many miles from another, and yet the ſame body to ariſe gloriouſly. We may believe it, but we are not able to conceive it. Now to the joyes of Heaven, <hi>Eye hath not ſeen, ear hath not heard, neither hath it entred into the heart of man to conceive the joyes that are there.</hi> The eye can ſee far,
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:150077:102"/>and the ear can hear far, the one can ſee the lightning afar off, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hear the thunder; yet eye and ear are both dull and heavy, if you bring them to the conſideration of this thing; here are things unuttera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, <hi>I was rapt up into the third Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Paul, and I ſaw things that were unutterable.</hi> And ſo for the Scriptures, though in all things neceſſary to ſalvation, the Scriptures are plain and evident; but take many places of the Scripture, how far remote are they from our underſtanding? what great myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries are there? One being asked what God was, took firſt a day, then two, then three dayes, then four, and ſo the farther he went to ſearch, the more he was plunged; So in the Scriptures, ſome places are plain, a Lamb may feed in them. In pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies, we fix upon one man, he muſt be the deliverer; we ſee him taken from the world, and the work
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:150077:103"/>left undone. The beſt Comment upon prophecies is the fulfilling of them. Look upon ſome other Texts of Scripture; What ſhould they do that are baptized for the dead, if the dead riſe not up again? Becauſe of the Angels the women muſt be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt. Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> did not know it, and that's in regard of the Scripture, <hi>We know but in part.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, in regard of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, what we know, we know after an imperfect partial faſhion; and therefore it is, Beloved, that Faith ſhould be embraced by us, becauſe we believe that we cannot under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand. Hence it is that we have but an opinion of many things in the world: If there were certain know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, what needed opinion?</p>
            <p>Fourthly, becauſe we do admire all things; there's no admiration but where there wants underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Thus it is in the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> diſplay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto you; I might proceed fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:150077:103"/>in ſeveral kindes of knowledge among Heathens and Chriſtians: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Heathens, they do worſhip an unknown God; there was an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar in <hi>Athens</hi> dedicated, with this Inſcription, <hi>To the unknown God, Acts</hi> 17. They do worſhip they know not what, as our Saviour ſpeaks to the Samaritan woman: <hi>You worſhip you know not what;</hi> and they do feel and grope after God, if perhaps they can finde him. There was one <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius,</hi> that having read <hi>Platoes</hi> Works of the Immortality of the ſoul, and having often read them uſed theſe words, <hi>Neſcio,</hi> &amp;c. I know not how, but when I am rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding I give aſſent, when I have laid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the Book all ſlips from me; ſo doting is our knowledge, for the earthly man, the carnal man diſcerns not the things that are Gods, nay, for the beſt they ſee but through a glaſs, they ſee but in part. Thus you ſee the points laid open unto
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:150077:104"/>you, I will bring it home to your Conſciences a little in the applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and then I ſhall conclude. Some there are that do oppoſe this truth, others that pervert it.</p>
            <p>Some there are that oppoſe it, and thoſe are our adverſaries the Romaniſts: Firſt, in ſetting up the infallibility of the Pope; and ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in crying up the Fathers and the Councels for our Faith. How can this be but falſe, if this be true that we know but in part?</p>
            <p>Firſt, therefore for the infallibility of the Pope, who will ſit like an Emperour and take up any contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie; Beloved, we know contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies on foot which he cannot decide, between the Franciſcans and Dominicans, about the Aſſumption of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and the like; either he cannot or dares not end them for fear of loſing either ſide; but <hi>we know but in part.</hi> Have not ſome of their Popes been pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:150077:104"/>Hereticks by General Councels? and yet theſe men muſt know all things. One of them could not read Saint <hi>Matthews</hi> Goſpel, and yet theſe muſt be ſaved; they would pluck out their own eyes, and ſee by other mens; and how can this be, if as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>we know but in part?</hi> And then again, they will cry up the Fathers and Councels, but when all is done they do but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe us, and the Fathers will be found to erre when all comes to light. Were there not ſome of them that held dangerous and Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical opinions? But I am loth to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover our forefathers nakedneſs: If I muſt, I will take you off from ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it, riſing up to it, and too much reverencing it. <hi>Cyprian</hi> was for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptization, Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> was once of opinion that children ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Sacrament of the Lords Supper as well as others of age; and <hi>Origen</hi> was of opinion that Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:150077:105"/>had hands, and fleſh, and eyes; and <hi>Juſtin Martyr:</hi> but I rather co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them in ſilence, but that the Papiſts do incite us; the Fathers were but a partial, no infallible rule.</p>
            <p>Again, as ſome do oppoſe this point, ſo ſome do pervert it: So the Papiſts they pervert it, and ſay, Becauſe <hi>we know but in part,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt have Traditions, for <hi>we know but in part,</hi> as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith. In this they do but as we ſay, bring coals to <hi>New-Caſtle,</hi> or light a candle to the Sun, by bringing their Traditions to be proved by this Scripture.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the Anabaptiſts, they pervert it, and conclude from hence, becauſe <hi>we know but in part,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we will look for revelation from above; and thereupon they caſt by the Book of God, and look for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations from Heaven. God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid we ſhould countenance any ſuch
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:150077:105"/>ſpirits as theſe are, for what is there to be known but what is fetcht out of Gods Word.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, others forſooth, that are lazy Chriſtians, will ſay, If I turn over the Book of God never ſo much, I ſhall <hi>know but in part,</hi> therefore I will know nothing at all: Like little children, if you take away one of their trinkets, they will throw all the reſt away: Or, becauſe one man gives me a box on the ear, therefore I will ſue him, and becauſe I may not have five hundred pounds damages, therefore I will have nothing at all. This is like the Hangman, that firſt blindes the malefactors eyes, and then turns him off. This was it made the Jews crucifie the Lord of life, for had they known it they would not have done it. The candle muſt be put out, or elſe put into the dark Lanthorn (ſay the Papiſts) we muſt not ſee what miſchiefs are towards. This ignorance muſt needs be the
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:150077:106"/>way to Hell, to utter darkneſs.</p>
            <p>If <hi>we know but in part,</hi> Firſt, let us follow men but in part. Turn over Antiquity, borrow authority from the Fathers, they will be good moral perſwaſions and inductions to bring us to the truth, but bring all to the Scripture, weigh it by the ballance of the Sanctuary, whether it be good or no. And where they ſpeak that which is contradictory to the Word of God, let us prefer Truth before the Fathers. Chriſt ſaith not, I am Antiquity, or I am Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, but <hi>I am Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, if <hi>we know but in part,</hi> let us add ſome cubits to our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. Knowledge is like unto Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, it is very glorious if we could ſee it; and we muſt firſt know the will of our Father before we can do it. This is the firſt ſtep to know what God is, and to know what our ſelves are. Firſt, begin with know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, then go on with practice:
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:150077:106"/>Firſt, know the truth, and then ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to it, and then defend it to the death.</p>
            <p>Let us add knowledg unto our knowledg, but as <hi>we know but in part,</hi> let us be wiſe alſo, take heed of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring roughly into the cabinets of God, we muſt not gaze too high.</p>
            <p>I do not ſay but that we ſhould ſearch the myſteries of the Word of God, and ſtudy them freely; but what myſteries God hath reſerved unto himſelf, meddle not with them, <hi>we know but in part.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And then again, make amends for thy want of knowledg by thy faith; believe, if God hath ſaid it, ſet thy ſeal of faith unto it. He (ſaith <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>) that will be wiſe in <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> is a fool in Chriſt. And a Pope did once ſay, that <hi>Piſcatores</hi> and not Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers were to be believed; they that ſay they know much, know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul.</hi> The emptieſt hogſheads ſound moſt,
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:150077:107"/>and the ſhalloweſt waters make the greateſt noiſe, <hi>Non eſt, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is no true knowledg, but a ſwelling and excreſcency.</p>
            <p>In the ſixth place, we muſt pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe what we know; if <hi>we know but in part,</hi> let us make amends for our partial knowledg in practiſing what we know, and whatſoever elſe you know, be ſure to know thoſe things that concern your eternal ſalvation. What is it for men to be ſcrupulous in leaving out <hi>H</hi> in <hi>Homo,</hi> and yet will take away a man. This is the onely true Arithmetick, <hi>to number our dayes, that we may apply our hearts unto wiſdome,</hi> that's the true Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy. This is it indeed that we muſt diſcourſe of. What is it then to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve our Supremacy in Logick, to be overcome in Arithmetick, to talk of Generation, and have not Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration? It is not enough to know, but we muſt practiſe. <hi>If you know theſe things, happy are you if
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:150077:107"/>you do them.</hi> Beloved, how many Sermons have been loſt in this place, and in divers other places of this Kingdome? what will you hear and devour all, and bring forth no fruit at all? for ſhame make it up by your practice; he that practiſeth what he knows, God will make him to know more; ſome know to inſtruct others, that's charity; ſome know to practice, and that's piety; ſome know for affectation, and that's pride. Knowledge makes a man worſe rather then better, unleſs he practiſe. Knowledg like the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corns horn, doth well in a mans hand, but ill in a beaſts head. A man that's ignorant, he carries <hi>Uriah</hi>'s letters in his own boſome. <hi>They that know and do not practiſe, ſhall be beaten with many ſtripes.</hi> What canſt thou ſay in excuſe of thy ſelf? thou ſeeſt the Sun-ſhine of the Goſpel, thou art not in darkneſs as many are; if thou doſt not practiſe it, woe be unto thee.
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:150077:108"/>We have had the light of the Goſpel above theſe threeſcore years, and what excuſe can we make?</p>
            <p>Laſtly, let us hunger and long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that place where we ſhall ſee God face to face, where there ſhall be no darkneſs without, nor darkneſs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, where the walls are made of chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtal, and the gates of pearl. There is no need of the Sun, nor of the Moon, nor of the Stars, God is the Light, and the Lamb is the Light; of it, and to that place God of his mercy bring us for his mercy ſake, for his Sons ſake, and for our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt his ſake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:150077:108"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150077:109"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150077:109"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
